<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The traytor a tragedy : with alterations, amendments and additions / written by Mr. Rivers.</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13788878</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13788878</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 849:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The traytor a tragedy : with alterations, amendments and additions / written by Mr. Rivers.</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
                  <author>Rivers, Mr. (Antony)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Parker ... and Sam. Briscoe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Writtten by James Shirley, not by Anthony Rivers. Cf. DNB; NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Licensed as by Shirely and printed in 1635 under his name.  Motteux (1692) ascribed the work to the Jesuit Rivers (d. 1626); but Gillow thinks Anthony Rivers, "vere Whitelock," who died in Newgate after 1635 more probable.  The ascription to Rivers is discredited by Dyce and others.  Cf. J. Gillow, Biog. dict. of English Catholics, v. 5, p. 428-429; A.H. Nason, James Shirley, 1915, p. 432.</note>
                  <note>"As it is now acted at the Theatre Royal, by Their Majesties servants."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101820:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101820:1"/>
            <p>THE TRAYTOR. A TRAGEDY: WITH Alterations, Amendments, and Additions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As it is now Acted at the Theatre Royal, by their Majeſties Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by Mr. <hi>Rivers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Parker</hi> at the Royal <hi>Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Sam. Briſcoe</hi> in <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> over againſt <hi>Wills Coffee-Houſe.</hi> MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101820:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101820:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable Donnogh Earl of <hi>Clancarty,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Muſkery,</hi> and Baron <hi>Blarney.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Honour.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO Pardon my Boldneſs in Preſuming to ſhelter this Orphan under your Lordſhips Protection, I am not ignorant, having never as yet deſerved any Favour from you, that it cannot but meet with a ſevere Conſtruction, but wholly relying upon your Clemency<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who have always been a favourer of the Muſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I flatter my ſelf that your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lordſhip may, for the Authors ſake, vouchſafe to grant it a favourable acceptance. I will not ſlander it with my Praiſe, it is Commendation enough, to ſay the Author was Mr. <hi>Rivers.</hi> I am very well aſſur'd, after your peruſal your Honour will eſteem it one of the beſt Tragedies that this Age hath Produc'd. I humbly beg your Lordſhip to pardon this Preſumption,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Of your Honours moſt Humble And moſt Obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:101820:3"/>
            <head>The Perſons Names.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>Duke of <hi>Florence.</hi>
                     </label> Mr. <hi>Hodgſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> His Kinſman and Favorite the Traitor.</label> Mr. <hi>Kynaſton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> Brother to <hi>Amidea.</hi>
                     </label> Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Piſano,</hi> Lover to <hi>Oriana.</hi>
                     </label> Mr. <hi>Cibber.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Coſino,</hi> His Friend.</label> Mr. <hi>Harris.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Florio Sciarrhas</hi> brother.</label> Mr. <hi>Alexander.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Depazzi,</hi> A creature of <hi>Lorenzos.</hi>
                     </label> Mr. <hi>Haynes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Frederico,</label> Mr. <hi>Mich Lee.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Alonzo,</hi> Noblemen.</label> Mr. <hi>Bright.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Petruchio, Piſanoes</hi> Servant.</label> Mr. <hi>Freeman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Rogero,</hi> Page to <hi>Depazzi,</hi>
                     </label> Tommy <hi>Ken.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gentlemen,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Servants.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Amidea, Sciarrhas</hi> Siſter.</label> Mrs. <hi>Bracegirdle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Oriana,</hi> Beloved of <hi>Piſano.</hi>
                     </label> Mrs. <hi>Laſſells.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Moroſſa,</hi> Her Mother.</label> Mrs. <hi>Cory.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Luſt, Pleaſure. Furies.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101820:3"/>
            <head>THE TRAYTOR.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus Primus.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Piſano</hi> and <hi>Petruchio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſano.</speaker>
                  <p>DIDST bid him come?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>I did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Go back again,</l>
                     <l>And tell him, I am gone abroad.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>He's here already Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Coſino.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Piſano,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let me enfold thee thus:</l>
                     <l>And yet my heart counts this Embrace a diſtance.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I was woing <hi>Coſmo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Man, to tell thee, I was gone abroad</l>
                     <l>Before thou cam'ſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How's this? Your words and looks</l>
                     <l>Are ſtrange, and teach me to infer I am</l>
                     <l>Not welcome, that on riper Counſel, you</l>
                     <l>Do wiſh my abſence.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101820:4"/>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What for telling truth?</l>
                     <l>He thus ſhould have but made the fit to ſee</l>
                     <l>Thy friend, thou com'ſt with expectation</l>
                     <l>To hear me talk, as I was wont of State,</l>
                     <l>Our Friendſhip or of Women, <hi>Coſmo</hi> Yes: no ſuch matter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This is more wild than uſual, your language</l>
                     <l>Is not ſo clear as it was wont.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Right, right <hi>Coſmo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The reaſon is, I have ſtraggled,</l>
                     <l>And loſt my ſelf I know not where, in what</l>
                     <l>Part of the World, and would not this be ſhown</l>
                     <l>As well in him, to have prepar'd thee now?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>What humour's this <hi>Piſano,</hi> I am yet to underſtand?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To underſtand!</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt not underſtand me, yet thou haſt</l>
                     <l>A name in <hi>Florence,</hi> for a ripe young man,</l>
                     <l>Of nimble apprehenſion, of a wiſe</l>
                     <l>And ſpreading obſervation, of whom</l>
                     <l>Already our old Men do Propheſie</l>
                     <l>Good, and great things, worthy thy fair dimenſions.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This is an argument above the reſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Piſano</hi> is not well; for being temperate,</l>
                     <l>He was not wont to flatter, and abuſe</l>
                     <l>His Friend.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Beſides there is another reaſon,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhould'ſt diſcover me at heart, through all</l>
                     <l>Theſe miſts, thou art in Love too, and who cannot,</l>
                     <l>That feels himſelf the heat, but ſhrewdly gueſs</l>
                     <l>At every ſymptom of that wanton Feaver,</l>
                     <l>Oh my Friend!</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What misfortune can approach</l>
                     <l>Your happy Love in Faireſt <hi>Amidea.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let jealous Lovers fear, and feel what 'tis</l>
                     <l>To Languiſh, talk away their Blood, and Strength,</l>
                     <l>Queſtion their unkind Stars. You have your Game</l>
                     <l>Before you Sir.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Before me where? why doſt</l>
                     <l>Thou mock me <hi>Coſmo?</hi> Shee's not hero.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſmo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is</l>
                     <l>No Pilgrimage to travel to her Lip.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis not for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How Sir, for me? y've no</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101820:4"/>
                     <l>Suſpition, I can be guilty of</l>
                     <l>A Treaſon to our Friendſhip, be ſo juſt,</l>
                     <l>If malice have been buſie, with my fame,</l>
                     <l>To let me know—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You haſtily interpret,</l>
                     <l>Thy pardon I have only err'd, but not</l>
                     <l>With the leaſt ſcruple of thy faith, and honour</l>
                     <l>To me, thou haſt a noble Soul, and lov'ſt me</l>
                     <l>Rather too well, I would thou wer't my Enemy,</l>
                     <l>That we had been born in diſtant climates, and never</l>
                     <l>Took Cement from our Simpathies in Nature.</l>
                     <l>Would we had never ſeen, or known each other,</l>
                     <l>This may ſeem ſtrange, from him that loves thee <hi>Coſmo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>More pretious than his Life.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Love me, and wiſh</l>
                     <l>This ſeparation?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I will give thee proof;</l>
                     <l>So well I love thee, nothing in the world</l>
                     <l>Thy Soul doth heartily affect, but I</l>
                     <l>Do love it too, does it not trouble thy</l>
                     <l>Belief? I wear not my own heart about me,</l>
                     <l>But thine exchang'd, thy eyes let in my objects,</l>
                     <l>Thou hear'ſt for me, talk'ſt, kiſſeſt, and enjoyeſt</l>
                     <l>All my felicities.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>What means this Language?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But what's all this to thee? Go to <hi>Oriana,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And bath thy Lips in Roſie dew of kiſſes;</l>
                     <l>And if at thy return thou find'ſt I have a being</l>
                     <l>In this vain world, 'Ile tell thee more.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, you muſt not part ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not with my good will,</l>
                     <l>I have no great ambition to be Mad.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Petruchio,</hi> let me conjure thee, tell</l>
                     <l>What weight hangs on thy Maſters heart? why does he</l>
                     <l>Appear ſo full of Trouble?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ye not gueſs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>Why he loves—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>The Beauteous <hi>Amidea,</hi> I know that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some ſuch thing was, But you are his Friend My L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>His Soul is now devoted to <hi>Oriana.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And he will dye for her, if this Ague hold him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101820:5"/>
                  <speaker>Coſmo,</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ha!</l>
                     <l>For 'tis not poſſible without ſome cure,</l>
                     <l>He ſhould live long:</l>
                     <l>Good Sir, do you go in and Counſel him.</l>
                     <l>So, ſo, it works;</l>
                     <l>This was my Lord <hi>Lorenzoes</hi> Plot, and I</l>
                     <l>Ha' been his Engine in the work, to batter.</l>
                     <l>His love to <hi>Amidea,</hi> by prayſing</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oriana</hi> to him, he is here, My Lord.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit <hi>Coſ.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petruchio,</hi> where's your Lord? how moves the work<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To your own wiſh My Lord, he has thrown off</l>
                     <l>The thought of <hi>Amedia,</hi> and is mad</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Coſmo</hi>'s Miſtreſs, whom by your inſtructions</l>
                     <l>I have commended ſo—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>My witty Villain!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Coſmo</hi> is with him, to whom cunningly</l>
                     <l>I ha' diſcover'd his diſeaſe, and I</l>
                     <l>Beſeech you interrupt 'em not.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This may</l>
                     <l>Have Tragical effects <hi>Petruchio:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For <hi>Coſmo,</hi> we ſhall prune his fortune thus,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oriana</hi>'s wealth would ſwell him in the State,</l>
                     <l>He growes too faſt already, be ſtill ours.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord, you bought my Life, when you procur'd</l>
                     <l>My pardon from the Duke.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Pet.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Piſa.</hi> and <hi>Coſmo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Friend, thou canſt not be ſo merciful,</l>
                     <l>To give away ſuch happineſs, my Love</l>
                     <l>Is for ſome ſin I have committed, thus</l>
                     <l>Tranſplanted, I look'd rather thou ſhouldſt kill me,</l>
                     <l>Then give away this comfort, 'tis a charity</l>
                     <l>Will make thee poor, and 'twere a great deal better</l>
                     <l>That I ſhould languiſh ſtill, and die.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oriana</hi> and I were but in Treaty.</l>
                     <l>If you can find diſpenſation, to quit</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Amidea,</hi> your firſt Love, be confident</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oriana</hi> may be wone, and it were neceſſary</l>
                     <l>You did prepare the Mother.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101820:5"/>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Each ſillable is a bleſſing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Although ſome complaints have paſt between</l>
                     <l>Me and <hi>Oriana,</hi> I am not warm</l>
                     <l>Yet in the Mothers fancy, whoſe power may</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſt you much, but looſe no time.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou Miracle of Friendſhip!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Duke <hi>Frederico, Florio,</hi> and <hi>Alonſo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Letters to us? from whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Caſtruchio.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>The Exile, whence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scienna</hi> My good Lord,</l>
                     <l>It came inclos'd within my Letter, which</l>
                     <l>Impos'd my care and duty in the ſwift Delivery.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>The Duke is pale of the ſuddain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Palſie does poſſeſs me, Ha! <hi>Lorenzo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our Couſin, the Enemy of Our Life and State,</l>
                     <l>My boſom Kinſman? not too loud, the Traytor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>May hear, and by eſcape prevent Our Juſtice.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>What Traytor?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alonſo,</hi> come you hither,</l>
                     <l>What correſpondency maintain you with this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtruchio?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>None My Lord, but I am happy</l>
                     <l>In his election, to bring the firſt</l>
                     <l>Voice to your ſafety.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Moſt ingrateful man!</l>
                     <l>Turn Rebel: I have worn him in my blood.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis time to purge the humour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>I will do't.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our Guard, were he more precious, had he ſhar'e</l>
                     <l>Our ſoul, as he but borrows of our fleſh,</l>
                     <l>This action makes him nothing.</l>
                     <l>He turne conſpirator: Oh the fate of Princes!</l>
                     <l>But ſtay, this paper ſpeakes of no particular,</l>
                     <l>He does not mention what deſign, what plot.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>More Providence is neceſſary,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Right, right, good <hi>Alonſo,</hi> th' art an honeſt man</l>
                     <l>And lov'ſt us well, what's to be done?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis beſt</l>
                     <l>To make his perſon ſure, by this you may</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101820:6"/>
                     <l>Diſcover ſooneſt who are of his faction—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And at our leiſure ſtudy of his puniſhment,</l>
                     <l>Which muſt exceed death; every common treſpaſs</l>
                     <l>Is ſo rewarded, firſt apply all tortures</l>
                     <l>To inforce confeſſion, who are his confederates,</l>
                     <l>And how they meant to murder us, then ſome rare</l>
                     <l>Invention to execute the Traytor,</l>
                     <l>So as he may be half a year a dying,</l>
                     <l>Will make us fam'd for Juſtice.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Lorenzo, Depazzi.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He is here,</l>
                     <l>Shal's apprehend him?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Happy morning to</l>
                     <l>My gratious Soveraign.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Can Treaſon couch it ſelf within that frame?</l>
                     <l>We ha' Letters for you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Letters, theſe dread Sir</l>
                     <l>Have no directions to me, your Highneſs</l>
                     <l>Is only nam'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They will concern your reading,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alonſo,</hi> now obſerve and watch him <hi>Florio,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Depazzi</hi> come you hither, does <hi>Lorenzo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Look like a Traitor?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſir, a Traytor?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſir by my Honour not I ſir, I defie</l>
                     <l>Him that ſpeaks it; I am in a fine pickle.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>I ha' read—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>No bluſh! not tremble: Read again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ſubſtance is, that you maintain</l>
                     <l>A vigilant eye over <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> who</l>
                     <l>Hath threatned with your death, his Countries liberty</l>
                     <l>And other things, touching reducing of</l>
                     <l>A Common-wealth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>I like not that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All's out:</l>
                     <l>A pox upon him for a Traytor, he</l>
                     <l>Has hedg'd me in but 'Ile confeſs—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What anſwer</l>
                     <l>Make you to this <hi>Lorenzo?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101820:6"/>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This o'th' ſuddain.</l>
                     <l>Sir I muſt owe the title of a Traitor</l>
                     <l>To your high favours; Envy firſt conſpir'd,</l>
                     <l>And malice now accuſes, but what ſtory,</l>
                     <l>Mentioned his name, that had his Princes boſome,</l>
                     <l>Without the Peoples hate, 'tis ſin enough</l>
                     <l>In ſome men to be great, the throng of ſtars</l>
                     <l>The rout, and common People of the skie,</l>
                     <l>Move ſtill another way then the Sun does,</l>
                     <l>That guilds the creature, take your honors back,</l>
                     <l>And if you can that purple of my veins,</l>
                     <l>Which flowes in yours, and you ſhall leave me in</l>
                     <l>A ſtate, I ſh'anot fear the great ones envy,</l>
                     <l>Nor common peoples rage, and yet perhaps</l>
                     <l>You may be credulous againſt me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> is cool.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alonzo</hi> look you prove.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lorenzo</hi> what you ſay.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſay my Lord?</l>
                     <l>I have diſcovered all my knowledge ſir:</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Stand to't—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With licence of your highneſs, what</l>
                     <l>Can you imagine I ſhould gain by Treaſon:</l>
                     <l>Admit I ſhould be impious, as to kill you,</l>
                     <l>I am your neareſt kinſman, and ſhould forfeit</l>
                     <l>Both name and future title to the State,</l>
                     <l>By ſuch a haſty, bloody diſpoſition,</l>
                     <l>The rabble hate me now, how ſhall I then</l>
                     <l>Expect a ſafety? is it reformation:</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Florence</hi> they accuſe me of; ſuggeſting</l>
                     <l>I diſaffect a Monarchy, which how</l>
                     <l>Vain and ridiculous would appear in me,</l>
                     <l>Your wiſdom judge, in you I live and flouriſh,</l>
                     <l>What in your death can I expect, to equal</l>
                     <l>The riches I enjoy under your warm'th?</l>
                     <l>Should I for the heir, and talk of new government,</l>
                     <l>And Common-wealth, looſe all my certainties?</l>
                     <l>And you above 'em all, whoſe favours have</l>
                     <l>Fall'n like the Dew upon me; have I a ſoul</l>
                     <l>to think the guilt of ſuch a murder eaſie,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101820:7"/>
                     <l>Were there no other Torments? Or can I</l>
                     <l>Expect the People will reward your Murderer</l>
                     <l>With any thing but Death, a Paricide?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>So, ſo, the <hi>Duke</hi>'s already in his circle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But I am tame, as if I had no ſence,</l>
                     <l>Nor other argument to vindicate</l>
                     <l>My Loyalty, thus poyſoned by a paper,</l>
                     <l>In my eternal fame, and by a ſlave;</l>
                     <l>Call to my brow, ſome one that dare accuſe me,</l>
                     <l>Let him have honour, great as mine, to forfeit;</l>
                     <l>Or ſince your grace hath taken me ſo near,</l>
                     <l>Your own height, that may ſcale, may not expect</l>
                     <l>Such a proportioned adverſary, yet let him</l>
                     <l>Have name within his Country, and allow him</l>
                     <l>A Soul, 'gainſt which, I may ingage my more,</l>
                     <l>Then equal honor, then I'll praiſe your juſtice;</l>
                     <l>But let him not be one condemned already,</l>
                     <l>A deſperate exile—is it poſſible</l>
                     <l>A Treaſon hatcht in <hi>Florence,</hi> 'gainſt the Duke</l>
                     <l>Should have no eyes at home to penetrate,</l>
                     <l>The growing danger, but at <hi>Sienna,</hi> one</l>
                     <l>Muſt with a perſpective diſcover all:</l>
                     <l>Ask this good Councellor, or theſe Gentlemen</l>
                     <l>Whoſe faiths are tried, whoſe cares are always waking</l>
                     <l>About your Perſon, how have I appear'd</l>
                     <l>To them, that thus I ſhould be rendered hateful,</l>
                     <l>To you, and my good Country, they are vertuous,</l>
                     <l>And dare not blemiſh a white faith, accuſe</l>
                     <l>My ſound heart of diſhonor; ſir, you muſt</l>
                     <l>Pardon my bold defence, my vertue bleeds</l>
                     <l>By your much eaſineſs, and I am compell'd</l>
                     <l>To break all modeſt limits, and to waken</l>
                     <l>Your memory, (if it be not too late</l>
                     <l>To ſay you have one,) with the ſtory of</l>
                     <l>My fair deſervings, who, ſir, overthrew</l>
                     <l>(With his deſigns) your late ambitious brother,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hippolito,</hi> who like a Meteor threatned</l>
                     <l>A black and fatal omen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be yet as juſt, and ſay whoſe art directed</l>
                     <l>A countermine to check the pregnant hopes</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Salviati,</hi> who for his Cardinals Cap,</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101820:7"/>
                     <l>In <hi>Rome</hi> was potent, and here popular.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>None but <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Admirable Traitor?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whoſe ſervice was commended when the exiles</l>
                     <l>One of whoſe tribe accuſeth me had raiſed</l>
                     <l>Commotions in our <hi>Florence</hi> when the hinge</l>
                     <l>Of State did faint under the burthen, and</l>
                     <l>The people ſweat with their own fears, to think</l>
                     <l>The Souldier ſhould inhabit their calm dwellings?</l>
                     <l>Who then roſe up your ſafety, and cruſh'd all</l>
                     <l>Their plots to ayre?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Our dear Couſin <hi>Lorenzo,</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When he that ſhould reward, forgets the men</l>
                     <l>That purchas'd his ſecurity, 'tis vertue</l>
                     <l>To boaſt a merit with my ſervices</l>
                     <l>I ha'not ſtarved your treaſury, the grand</l>
                     <l>Captain <hi>Gonzales</hi> accounted to King <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Three hundred thouſand crowns, for ſpies, what bills</l>
                     <l>Have I brought in for ſuch intelligence:</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I grow hearty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All thy actions</l>
                     <l>Stand freſh before us, and confirm, thou art</l>
                     <l>Our beſt and deareſt friend, thus we aſſure</l>
                     <l>Our confidence, they love us not that feed</l>
                     <l>One jealous thought of our dear Couſ. <hi>Lorenzo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>New welcome to us all, for you <hi>Alonzo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Give o're your paper kites, learn wit, 'tis time.</l>
                     <l>Where ſhall we meet to night?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon me ſir I am a dangerous man</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No more a that</l>
                     <l>I'll credit my ſoul with thee, ſhall we revel</l>
                     <l>This night with <hi>Amidea?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Duke</hi> courts him,</l>
                     <l>Well go thy ways, for one of the moſt excellent</l>
                     <l>Impudent Traitors—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet a murmuring</l>
                     <l>Of a Traitor? we ſhall ſooner ſuſpect him,</l>
                     <l>That thinks <hi>Lorenzo</hi> guilty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I my Lord</l>
                     <l>Dare boldly ſwear, his honour is as free—</l>
                     <l>From any treaſon, as my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>I did propheſie this iſſue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis an age</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101820:8"/>
                     <l>Till night, I long to fold her in my armes,</l>
                     <l>Prepare <hi>Sciarrah,</hi> but be very wiſe</l>
                     <l>In the diſcovery, he is all touchwood.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know he is her brother, leave the managing</l>
                     <l>Of things to me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Still when we expect,</l>
                     <l>Our bliſs, time creeps, but when the happier things</l>
                     <l>Call to enjoy, each ſawcy hour hath wings.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Sciarrah,</hi> and <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sciarrah.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY Siſter, though he be the Duke, he dares not,</l>
                     <l>Patience, patience, if there be ſuch a vertue,</l>
                     <l>I want it Heaven, my Siſter!</l>
                     <l>It has thrown wild-fire in my brain <hi>Lorenzo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A thouſand furies revel in my skull,</l>
                     <l>Has he not ſins enough in's Court to damn him.</l>
                     <l>But my Roof muſt be guilty of new luſts,</l>
                     <l>And none but <hi>Amidea?</hi> theſe the honours</l>
                     <l>His preſence brings our Houſe?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>Temper your rage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Are all the Brothels rifled? No quaint piece</l>
                     <l>Left him in <hi>Florence,</hi> that will meet his hot</l>
                     <l>And valiant Luxury, that we are come</l>
                     <l>To ſupply his blood out of our Families?</l>
                     <l>Diſeaſes gnaw his title off.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He is no Prince of mine, he forfeited</l>
                     <l>His greatneſs, that black minute he firſt gave</l>
                     <l>Conſent to my diſhonour.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I'm ſorry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why ſhould you be ſorry ſir?</l>
                     <l>You ſay it is my Siſter he would ſtrumpet,</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101820:8"/>
                     <l>Mine, <hi>Amidea?</hi> 'tis a wound you feel not,</l>
                     <l>But it ſtrikes through, and through the poor <hi>Sciarrah,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I do not think, but all the aſhes of</l>
                     <l>My Anceſtors do ſwell in their dark urnes</l>
                     <l>At this report, of <hi>Amidea</hi>'s ſhame:</l>
                     <l>It is their cauſe as well as mine, and ſhould</l>
                     <l>Heaven ſuffer the Duke's ſin to paſs unpuniſh'd,</l>
                     <l>Their duſt muſt of neceſſity conſpire,</l>
                     <l>To make an earth-quake in the Temple.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sir,</l>
                     <l>You ſaid you would hear me out.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why is there more</l>
                     <l>Behind?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And greater, Maſter, your high blood</l>
                     <l>Till I conclude <hi>Sciarrah,</hi> I accuſe not</l>
                     <l>Your noble anger, which I have obſerved,</l>
                     <l>Is not on every cheap, and giddy motion</l>
                     <l>Inflam'd, but Sir, be thrifty in your paſſion,</l>
                     <l>This is a petty treſpaſs,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Has miſchief any name</l>
                     <l>Beyond this? will it kill me with the ſound?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord, though the diſhonoring your Siſter,</l>
                     <l>Be ſuch a fact, the blood of any other</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Alexander</hi> could no leſs then expiate,</l>
                     <l>Yet this ſin ſtretches farther, and involves</l>
                     <l>With hers, your greater ſtain: did you e're promiſe him?</l>
                     <l>Yet why do I make any queſtion?</l>
                     <l>It were another crime, to think <hi>Sciarrah</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could entertain a thought, ſo far beneath</l>
                     <l>His birth, you ſtoop to ſuch a horrid baſeneſs,</l>
                     <l>Then all the vertue of mankind would ſicken,</l>
                     <l>And ſoon take leave of earth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>You torture me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What then could the Defind, to give him any</l>
                     <l>Encouragement you would be guilty of</l>
                     <l>And act, ſo fatal unto honor,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>To what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though all the teeming glories of his Dukedome,</l>
                     <l>Nay <hi>Florence</hi> State offered it ſelf a bribe,</l>
                     <l>Yet to imagine, you</l>
                     <l>Would turne officious pander to his luſt,</l>
                     <l>And interpoſe the mercenary bawd</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101820:9"/>
                     <l>To Court your Siſter to his ſinful coupling:</l>
                     <l>'Tis horrid, affrights nature, I grow ſtiff</l>
                     <l>With the imagination.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Hah!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet this was his command I ſhould impoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I am not what I was,</l>
                     <l>My ſoul is but one flame,</l>
                     <l>My breath is hot enough</l>
                     <l>To thaw the <hi>Alpes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your fancy would</l>
                     <l>Tranſport you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis my rage, but let it cool,</l>
                     <l>And then we'll talk o' ſomething, ſomething ſir,</l>
                     <l>Shall be to purpoſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now the flame is mounted,</l>
                     <l>My Lord, I have given proof, although he be</l>
                     <l>My Duke and Kinſman, I abhor his vices,</l>
                     <l>'Tis policy in Princes, to create</l>
                     <l>A Favorite, who muſt bear all the guilt</l>
                     <l>Of things ill manag'd in the State, if any</l>
                     <l>Deſign be happy, 'tis the Princes own.</l>
                     <l>Heavens knows, how I have covnſell'd this young man,</l>
                     <l>By vertue to prevent his fate, and govern</l>
                     <l>With modeſty: O the religious days<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of Common-wealths!</l>
                     <l>We have out-liv'd that bleſſing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But I have thought a cure for this great ſtate</l>
                     <l>Impoſtume.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To lance it, is't not ripe?</l>
                     <l>Let's draw cuts, whether your hand or mine</l>
                     <l>Shall do an act for <hi>Florence</hi> liberty,</l>
                     <l>And ſend this Tyrant to another world.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>How, I draw cuts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Toy it not thus <hi>Lorenzo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But anſwer, by the name and birth you are</l>
                     <l>His Kinſman;</l>
                     <l>And let me tell you more:</l>
                     <l>We know, you but diſguiſe your heart, and wiſh</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Florence</hi> would change her tile.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>How is this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We know you have firm correſpondence with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>The baniſht men, whoſe deſperate fortunes wait</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101820:9"/>
                     <l>Your call to tumult, in our ſtreets, all this,</l>
                     <l>Not to feed your ambition with a Dukedome,</l>
                     <l>By the remove of <hi>Alexander<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> but</l>
                     <l>To ſerve your Countrey, and create their peace,</l>
                     <l>Who groan under the Tyranny of a proud,</l>
                     <l>Laſcivious Monarch, is't not true <hi>Lorenzo?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My phraſe is blunt my Lord.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Genius</l>
                     <l>And thine are friends, I ſee they have convers'd</l>
                     <l>And I applaud the wiſdom of my ſtars,</l>
                     <l>That made me for his Friendſhip, who preſerves</l>
                     <l>The ſame religious fire, let this ſecret be</l>
                     <l>An argument, how much I dare repoſe</l>
                     <l>Upon <hi>Sciarrah</hi>'s honor,</l>
                     <l>I'll either live, in your exchange of faith</l>
                     <l>A Patriot, or die my Countries Martyr.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſt a fire beyond <hi>Prometheus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Heaven knows I've no particular deſign</l>
                     <l>To leap into a Throne, let me advance</l>
                     <l>Our liberty, reſtore the ancient Laws</l>
                     <l>Of the republick, reſcue from the jaws</l>
                     <l>Of luſt, your mothers, wives, your daughters, ſiſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Siſters!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>From horrid Rape, poor <hi>Amidea.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am reſolv'd, by all that's bleſt, he dies</l>
                     <l>The roof he would diſhonour with his luſt</l>
                     <l>Shall be his tombe, bid him be confident,</l>
                     <l>Conduct him good <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> I'll diſpoſe</l>
                     <l>My houſe for this great ſcene of death.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Be conſtant.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Florio,</hi> and his Siſter <hi>Amidea.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Now brother, what news brings the great <hi>Lorenzo?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let me have truce vexation for ſome minutes,</l>
                     <l>What news? preferments, honours, offices;</l>
                     <l>Siſter, you muſt to Court?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Who, I to Court?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or elſe the Court will come to you, the Duke</l>
                     <l>Hath ſent already for us <hi>Amidea:</hi> Is ſhe not fair,</l>
                     <l>Exceeding beautiful, and tempting <hi>Florio?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Look on her well, methinks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I could turn Poet,</l>
                     <l>And make her a more excellent piece then heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let not fond Men hereafter commend what</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101820:10"/>
                     <l>They moſt admire, by fetching from the Stars</l>
                     <l>Or flowers their glory of ſimilitute;</l>
                     <l>But from thy ſelf the rule to know all beauty,</l>
                     <l>Theſe are the Duke's own Raptures, <hi>Amidea,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His own Poetick flames, an argument</l>
                     <l>He loves my Siſter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>Love me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Infinitely,</l>
                     <l>I am in earneſt, he employ'd <hi>Lorenzo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No meaner Perſon in this Embaſſie,</l>
                     <l>You muſt to Court, Oh happineſs!</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>For what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What do great Ladies do at Court, I pray?</l>
                     <l>Enjoy the pleaſures of the world, dance, kiſs</l>
                     <l>The amorous Lords, and a thouſand more</l>
                     <l>Delights, which private Ladies never think of;</l>
                     <l>But above all,</l>
                     <l>The Duke himſelf ſhall call thee his,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You make me wonder,</l>
                     <l>Pray ſpeak that I may underſtand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come, come, I find your cunning;</l>
                     <l>The news does pleaſe, the rolling of your eye</l>
                     <l>Betrays you, and I ſee a guilty bluſh</l>
                     <l>Through this white veil upon your cheek, you wo'd</l>
                     <l>Have it confirm'd, you ſhall, the Duke himſelf</l>
                     <l>Shall ſwear he loves you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Love me? why?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To Court,</l>
                     <l>And ask him; be not you too peeviſh now,</l>
                     <l>And hinder all our fortune; I ha' promis'd him</l>
                     <l>To move you for his arm-ful, as I am</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrah,</hi> and your brother, more I ha<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſent</l>
                     <l>Word to him by <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> that you ſhould</l>
                     <l>Meet his high flame, in plain <hi>Italian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Love him, and—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>What for heaven, be the Duke's whore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, his Miſtriſs, command him, make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>Give up my Virgin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>honour to his luſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>You may give it a better name, but do't<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>I do miſtake you brother, do I not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, my meaning is ſo broad, you cannot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I would I did then, is't not poſſible</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101820:10"/>
                     <l>That this ſhould be a dream? where did you drop</l>
                     <l>Your vertue Sir? <hi>Florio,</hi> why move you not?</l>
                     <l>Why are you ſlow to tell this man? for ſure</l>
                     <l>'Tis not <hi>Sciarrah,</hi> he hath talk ſo ill,</l>
                     <l>And ſo much, that may have the cauſe to fear,</l>
                     <l>The Ayr about's infected.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Are not you</l>
                     <l>My brother?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be not you a Fool, to move</l>
                     <l>Theſe empty queſtions, but joyn to make her</l>
                     <l>Supple, and pliant for the Duke.</l>
                     <l>No matter for the talk of muſty people,</l>
                     <l>Look up to the Reward, thou art young and skill'd</l>
                     <l>In theſe Court temptings, naturally ſoft,</l>
                     <l>And moving, I am rough-hewn, aſſiſt, wo't,</l>
                     <l>With ſome queint Charm, to win her to this game?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>My Siſter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come not near him <hi>Florio,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis not <hi>Sciarrah,</hi> ſure my brothers Nurſe</l>
                     <l>Play'd the Impoſtor, and with ſome baſe Iſſue</l>
                     <l>Cheated our Houſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gipſie, uſe better language,</l>
                     <l>Or I'll forget your Sex.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Offer to touch her</l>
                     <l>With any rudeneſs, and by all that's vertuous—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Why how now Boy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I do not fear your Sword,</l>
                     <l>This with my Youth, and Innocence, is more</l>
                     <l>Defence than all thy armory, what Devil</l>
                     <l>Has crept into thy Soul?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>You'll not help?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile rather kill thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis very well,</l>
                     <l>Have you conſidr'd better o'the motion?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>And what's your reſolve</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To have my name</l>
                     <l>Stand in the Ivorie Regiſter of Virgins,</l>
                     <l>When I am dead, before one factious thought</l>
                     <l>Should lurk within me to betray my Fame,</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a blot, my hands ſhall mutiny,</l>
                     <l>And boldly with a Poniard teach my heart</l>
                     <l>To weep out a repentance.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He embraces 'em,</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101820:11"/>
                     <l>My excellent chaſt Siſter, <hi>Florio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou haſt my ſoul, I did but try your Vertues,</l>
                     <l>'Tis truth the <hi>Duke</hi> does love thee, vitiouſly,</l>
                     <l>This night he means to revel at our houſe,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Tarquin</hi> ſhall be entertained; he ſhall.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ent. a Serv.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, <hi>Piſano</hi> is come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Look up Siſter</l>
                     <l>And ſhine with thy own ſmiles, <hi>Piſano's</hi> come,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Piſano</hi> thy contracted, honour'd Friend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Piſano, Coſino, Freder.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Welcome all,</l>
                     <l>But you above the reſt, my brother ſhortly, <hi>Emb. him.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Siſter and <hi>Florio</hi> entertain your noble</l>
                     <l>Freinds, ſome few minute, I am abſent, we</l>
                     <l>Muſt not forget to prepare for the <hi>Dukes</hi> coming,</l>
                     <l>Ile ſoon return.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>You are not chearfull Sir.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How is't my Lord? you were not wont to look</l>
                     <l>So ſad when you came hither</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not well <hi>Amidea.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am,</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be you</l>
                     <l>Comforted Lady, let all griefs repair</l>
                     <l>To this, their proper Centur.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir how fare you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Altr'd of late a little, I wou'd <hi>Sciarra</hi> were come back.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I might ha' finiſh'd ere he went, and not</l>
                     <l>Delay'd his buſineſs much, two or three words,</l>
                     <l>And I had diſpatch'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How Sir? your language is</l>
                     <l>Another then you uſe to ſpeak, you look not</l>
                     <l>With the ſame brow upon me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Madam, I am come to render all my intereſt in your love,</l>
                     <l>And to demand my ſelf again live happier</l>
                     <l>In other Choice.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here's witneſs, all is cancel'd betwixt us,</l>
                     <l>Nay, and you weep—Farewell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                  <p>He's gone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>I am amaz'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Now lead me to my bleſſing.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeuni</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall a long ſuit and ſpeeding with his love</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With the worlds notice, and a general fame</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101820:11"/>
                     <l>Of Contract too, juſt in the Inſtant when</l>
                     <l>A Marriage is expected, he broke off</l>
                     <l>With Infamy to our Houſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Brother, If ever you lov'd poor <hi>Amidea,</hi> let not this</l>
                     <l>Arrive <hi>Sciarrhas</hi> Ear; there's danger in</l>
                     <l>His knowledge of it, this may be a Tryal of my Affection.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>A Tryal; No, It ſhewed too like a Truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>My Tears intreat your ſilence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You have Power to command it, dry your Eyes then,</l>
                     <l>He's return'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Sciarrha.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>How now, Weeping? Where is <hi>Piſano</hi> and his Friends?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>They'r gone, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gueſs by my Eyes, you may, ſomething of Sorrow hath befaln.</l>
                     <l>No ſooner you were departed, but ſome ſtrange Diſtemper</l>
                     <l>Invaded him; we might diſcern a change</l>
                     <l>In's Countenance: And though we pray'd him to</l>
                     <l>Repoſe with us, he would ſtrait back again;</l>
                     <l>So with <hi>Coſmo</hi> he return'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>The alteration was ſtrange and ſuddain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Las noble Gentleman,—but come, clear up</l>
                     <l>Your Face again, we hope it won't laſt;</l>
                     <l>Look bright again, I ſay, I ha' given order—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Gentleman.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord the Duke's already come</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Remove, Good <hi>Amidea,</hi> and reſerve thy Perſon</l>
                     <l>To Crown his Entertainment, be not ſeen yet.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Am.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Duke <hi>Lorenzo, Alonzo,</hi> Attendants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> we are come to be your Gueſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Highneſs doth an Honour to our Houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>But, where's thy Siſter, ſhe muſt did us wellcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>She is your Grace's Handmaid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>For this Night, Let the whole World conſpire to our delight. <hi>Lorenzo</hi>—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Whiſper.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir be confident—and periſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Moroſa,</hi> and <hi>Oriana,</hi> in the Garden, and Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pray give acceſs to none,—yet if <hi>Piſano</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Enqire, direct him to the Garden, <hi>Coſino</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Exit Servant.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is young, and promiſing, but while <hi>Lorenzo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lives, muſt expect no Sun-ſhine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Piſano, Coſmo,</hi> Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There's for thy paines.</l>
                     <stage>Evit Servant.</stage>
                     <l>They are now at opportunity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord,</l>
                     <l>Do you prepare the Mother, and let me cloſe with <hi>Oriana.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>What Service can reward thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Take occaſion to leave us private, This Hour be</l>
                     <l>Propitious, win but the Mother to you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101820:12"/>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>She is prepared alieady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Loſe no time, take the other walk.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Piſ. &amp; Mor.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear <hi>Coſmo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My beſt <hi>Oriana.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>You have been too much abſent, I muſt chide you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You cannot ſweet, I would knew which way to make thee.</l>
                     <l>Angry: Yes, that I might ſee how well it would become thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>You will make me angry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>But you will love me ſtill, I fear.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ye fear it? I'ſt a misfortune?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>My Love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>We may love too well, and that's a fault.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>Not where the Object's good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>O yes; Always beware of the extreams.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>What mean you? I affect none but my <hi>Coſmo,</hi> not him with too much Flame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>If you ſhould Lady, 'twere not nobly done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>To love another?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, if there be cauſe, that may be call'd a Vertae.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>So we ſhould be inconſtant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why not, it our reaſon be convinc'd.</l>
                     <l>Let us examine all the Creatures, read</l>
                     <l>The Book of Nature through, and we ſhall find</l>
                     <l>Nothing doth ſtill the ſame: Why then</l>
                     <l>Should our Deſires, that are ſo nimble, and</l>
                     <l>More Subtle than the Spirits in our Blood,</l>
                     <l>Be ſuch ſtaid Things within us, and not ſhare</l>
                     <l>Their natural Liberty, ſhall we admit a change in ſmaller Things,</l>
                     <l>And not allow it in what moſt of all concerns us?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Loves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Have you a ſuſpition I am changed, and thus would</l>
                     <l>School me for it, or ſhall I imagine that you are alter'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes, I am, and therefore proclaim thy Freedome,</l>
                     <l>I do love thee leſs, To ſhew I love thee more.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>What riddle's this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis none. I have found I am not worthy of thee,</l>
                     <l>Therefore come to make thee ſatisfaction for my Crime</l>
                     <l>Of loving thee, by pointing out a way,</l>
                     <l>And Perſon, will become thy Affection better.</l>
                     <l>What doſt think of brave <hi>Piſano,</hi> ſhall his Merit plead</l>
                     <l>Succeſſion in thy chaſt Thoughts?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>I know him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou can'ſt not chuſe; and I could ſtudy none</l>
                     <l>Worthy thy love, but him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis very likely you would reſign then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ay, to honour thee,</l>
                     <l>His Service will deſerve thee at the beſt,</l>
                     <l>And richeſt value.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101820:12"/>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>Why it ſhall be ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nay but be ſerious, and declare me happy</l>
                     <l>That I may ſay, I have made thee juſt amends.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſir I do love him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But doſt thou love him perfectly, with a</l>
                     <l>Deſire, when ſacred rites of marriage</l>
                     <l>Are paſt, to meet him in thy bed, and call him</l>
                     <l>Thy Husband?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pray tell me;</l>
                     <l>But truly, I beſeech you, do you wiſh</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Piſano</hi> mine indeed? or, are you jealous,</l>
                     <l>And name him to accuſe me?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not by goodneſs;</l>
                     <l>But if there be a charm beyond thy innocenſe,</l>
                     <l>By that I would conjure thee <hi>Oriana,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Love him and make three happy, it ſhall be</l>
                     <l>My bliſs to call you his, let me but own</l>
                     <l>A ſervant in your memory.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Unkind,</l>
                     <l>And cruel <hi>Coſmo,</hi> doſt thou think it poſſible,</l>
                     <l>I can love any thy ſelf? thou wilt</l>
                     <l>Undo my heart for ever.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Piſano</hi> and <hi>Moroſſa.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You ſhall be</l>
                     <l>Ever moſt welcome, if I be her Mother,</l>
                     <l>She muſt declare obedience, <hi>Oriana</hi>—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Go chearfully, thy Mother calls,</l>
                     <l>Alas poor Lady,</l>
                     <l>I half repent me, ſince ſhe is ſo conſtant:</l>
                     <l>But a friends life weighs down all other love;</l>
                     <l>Beſide, I thus ſecure my Fate, <hi>Lorenzo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Threatens my ſpring, he is my enemy.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>You'll not compel aſſection?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No, but Court it</l>
                     <l>With honour, and religion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſhall forget the nature of a Parent,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs you ſhew more ſoftneſs, and regard</l>
                     <l>To what is urged, what promiſe could you make</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Coſmo,</hi> without me? or if you had—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here <hi>Coſmo</hi> doth give up all title to it,</l>
                     <l>I have no part in <hi>Oriana</hi> now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101820:13"/>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I've heard too much, do with me what you pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>I am all paſſive, nothing of my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>But an Obedience to Unhappineſs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Follow her <hi>Piſano.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou'rt all Friendſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Trace their warm ſteps, Virgins Reſolves are weak.</l>
                     <l>Leave not her Eyes, until you ſee Day break.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Depazzi</hi> and <hi>Rogero.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Depazzi.</speaker>
                  <p>ROgero?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rogero.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Make faſt the Chamber-door, ſtifle the Key-hole and the Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, I muſt diſcourſe of ſecret Matters, doſt thou ſmell nothing, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gero?</hi> ha?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Smell? not any thing, my Lord, to offend my Noſtril.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Come hither, what do the people talk abroad of me? Anſwer me juſtly, and to the Point, what do they ſay?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith, my Lord, they ſay that you are—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>They lie, I am not; they are a lowſy, impudent multitude; a many-headed, and many-horned generation, to ſay that I am—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>A noble Gentleman, a juſt and diſcreet Lord, and one that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to have his Honours without money.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh is that it? I thought the Rabble would have ſaid, I had been a Traytor, I am half mad certainly e're ſince I conſented to <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo;</hi> 'tis a very hard condition, that a Man muſt loſe his Head, to recompence the procuring of his Honours: What if I diſcover him to the Duke, ten to one, if <hi>Lorenzo</hi> come but to ſpeak, his Grace won't ha' the grace to believe me, and then I run the hazard to be thrown out of all atother ſide: 'tis ſafeſt to be a Traytor, hum, who is that you whiſper'd to?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>I whiſper?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Marry did you, Sirrah?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Not I, good faith, my Lord,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirrah, Sirrah, Sirrah, I ſmell a Rat behind the Hangings: Here's no body, ha? Are there no Trunks to convey ſecret Voices?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Lordſhip has a pair on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101820:13"/>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not like that Face i'th' Arras, a my Conſcience he points at me, a Pox upon this Treaſon, I have no ſtomack to't, I do ſee my ſelf upon a Scaffold, making a pitiful Speech already, I ſhall ha' my head cut off, ſeven years ago I laid my head upon a wager, I remember, and loſt it; let me ſee; it ſhall be ſo, 'tis good policy to be arm'd, <hi>Rogero,</hi> imagin I were a Traytor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I but ſay imagin, we may put the Caſe, and that I were appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended for a Traytor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Heaven defend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Heaven has ſomething elſe to do, than to defend Traytors: I ſay, Imagin I were brought to the Bar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Good my Lord, you brought to the Bar?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I will beat you, if you won't imagin at my bidding: I ſay, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I now were at the Bar to anſwer for my Life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Sir, that's as it happens; you muſt Imagin I will anſwer the beſt I can for my ſelf: conceive, I prithee, that theſe Chairs were Judges, moſt grave and venerable Beards and Faces at my Arraignment, and that thy ſelf wert in the Name of the Duke and State to accuſe me; what couldſt thou ſay to me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>I, accuſe your good Honour? for what, I beſeech you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>For High-Treaſon, you Blockhead.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt be acquainted with ſome Particulars firſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſs, thou ſayſt right: why imagin, dye hear? you muſt but imagin, that ſome great Man had a Conſpiracy againſt the Duke's perſon, and that I being an honeſt Lord, and one of this great Mans Friends, had been drawn in; for that's the plain truth on't, 'twas againſt my will, but that's all one: Well, thou underſtandſt me, ſhew thy wit <hi>Rogero,</hi> ſcratch thy nimble <hi>Pericranium,</hi> and thunder out my Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>ex tempore:</hi> Here I ſtand Signior <hi>Depazzi,</hi> to anſwer the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Good my Lord, it will not become me, being your humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Humble Coxcomb, is't not for my good? I ſay, accuſe me, bring it home, jerk me ſoundly to the quick, <hi>Rogero,</hi> tickle me, as thou lov'ſt thy Lord; I do defie thee, ſpare me not, and the Devil take thee if thou bee'ſt not malicious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then have at you: Firſt, Signior <hi>Depazzi,</hi> Thou art In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted of High-Treaſon, Hold up thy Hand, Guilty, or not Guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Very good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, very bad Sir; Anſwer, I ſay, Guilty or not Guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Not Guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101820:14"/>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis your beſt courſe to ſay ſo. Well, Imagin—I riſe up the Duke's moſt learned in the Laws, and his nimble tongu'd Orator, have at your Signior.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come on Sir, here I ſtand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>I will prove thou lieſt in thy Throat, if thou denieſt thy Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſo I addreſs my ſelf to the moſt underſtanding ſeats of Juſtice. Moſt wiſe, moſt honourable, and moſt uncorrupt Judges, ſleep not, I beſeech you, my Place hath call'd me to plead in the behalf of my Prince and Country, againſt this notable, this pernicious, and impudent Traytor, who hath plotted and contrived ſuch high, heinous and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Treaſons, as no Age nor Hiſtory hath ever mention'd the like. Here he ſtands, whoſe Birth I will not touch, becauſe its altogether unknown who begot him. He was brought up among the ſmall Wares in the City, became Rich by ſiniſter and indirect Practices, married a Merchant's Wife at adventures, and was ſoon after advanc'd to be a Head Officer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, you Raſcal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Peace, Sirrah, peace; nay, your Lordſhips ſhall find him very audacious: This Fellow, not content to have his Branches ſpread within the City, I ſpeak it to his Face, let him deny it, was afterward, by the corruption of his Conſederate, and the meer grace of his Highneſs, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Honour, received infinite Favours from his Prince of bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; yet, like a Wretch, a Villain, a Viper, a Rat of <hi>Nilus,</hi> he hath practiſed Treaſons againſt the ſacred perſon of the Duke: for which he deſerveth not only to die, but alſo to ſuffer Tortures, Whips, Racks, Strapadoes, Wheels, and all the fiery brazen Bulls that can be invented, as I ſhall make it appear to this honourable and illuſtrious Court.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>This Rogue's tranſported.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>With all my heart, I obey your Lordſhips—Thus then I paſs from theſe Circumſtances, and proceed to the principal Villanies that we have to lay to his charge. <hi>Imprimis,</hi> Thou Signior <hi>Depazzi</hi> didſt offer to a Groom a 100 Crowns to poyſon his Highneſs hunting Saddle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Did I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not interrupt me, Varlet, I will prove it, his hunting Saddle, and wo ſhall be unto thy breech therefore; and finding this ſerpentine Treaſon broken in the ſhell, do but lend your reverend Ears to his next deſigns, I will cut 'em off preſently. This Irreligious, nay, Atheiſtical Traytor, did with his own hands poyſon the Duke's Prayer Book, oh Impiety! And had his Highneſs, as in former times he accuſtomed, but pray'd once in a month, which by ſpecial grace he omitted, how
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101820:14"/>
fatal had it been to <hi>Florence?</hi> But as by Juſtice his Excellence did then, and by his own want of devotion, prevent this Aſſaſinates purpoſe, ſo we hope in his own Diſcretion, and the Council of his State, he will take heed how he prays hereafter while he lives, to which every true Subject will ſay, Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>May it pleaſe your Honors—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>That impudent, brazen-fac'd Traytor, wilt thou deny it? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, and like your good Lordſhips, he hath for this Fortnight, or Three Weeks before his Apprehenſion, walk'd up and down the Court with a Caſe of Piſtols charg'd, wherewith, as he partly confeſſed, he intended to ſend the Duke to Heaven with a powder.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>This Rogue will undo the Devil at Invention, may it pleaſe his Honourable—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are but ſprinklings of his Treaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you juſtifie this? Did I any of theſe things, you Tadpole?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold your ſelf contented, my Lord, he that is brought to the Bar in caſe of Treaſon, muſt look to have more objected than he can anſwer, or any Man is able to juſtify.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs, and pleaſe your good Lord ſhips.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Mark, he will confeſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>That's the way to be ſent of an headleſs Errand; indeed I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that I never intended any Treaſon to his Highneſs, nor ever ſought the Prince's Life: true it is, that I heard of a Conſpiracy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>That, that, my Lord, hath overthrown him; he ſaith, he never ſought the Prince's Life, <hi>Ergo,</hi> he ſought his Death. Beſides, he hath heard of Treaſon, now he that heareth, and diſcovereth not, is equally guilty in Fact: For in Offences of this Nature, there are not Acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; <hi>ergo,</hi> he is a Principal, and being a Principal Traitor, he deſerveth Condemnation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I not ſpeak?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Traitors muſt not be ſuffered to ſpeak, for when they have leave, they have Liberty, and he that is a Traitor deſerveth to be cloſe Priſoner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>All that this Fellow hath uttered, is falſe and forged, abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Lies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſpeak Truth, and I will be heard, and no man elſe in this place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I never dream'd of a hunting Saddle, nor never had ſo much as a thought of any Prayer Book.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:101820:15"/>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſit here to do Juſtice, I ſpeak for the Duke and the ſafety of the Common wealth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>As for Piſtols, 'tis well known I could never indure the report on 'em, I defie Powder and Shot, as I do him that accuſeth me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>I defie all the world that will hear a Traitor ſpeak, for himſelf, 'tis againſt the Law which provides that no Man ſhall defend treaſon, and he that ſpeaks for himſelf, being a Traitor, doth defend his treaſon, thou art a Capital obſtreperous Malefactor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art a Mad-man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Go to, you have play'd the fool too much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou continual motion ceaſe, a pox upon thee hold thy tongue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>The pox won't ſerve your turn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then this ſhall.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Beats him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, hold, good my Lord, I am ſenſible I ha done, imagine I ha done, I but obey'd your Lordſhip, whoſe batoon I find ſtronger than my imagination, my Lord, you'll anſwer this to ſtrike i'the' Court thus?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I am as weary—heark <hi>Rogero</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Knocks.</stage>
                  <p>One knocks, ſee, ſee, there's to make thee amendends, ſee good <hi>Rogero,</hi> and ſay nothing, pray Heaven it be not Purſevant.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Petruchio,</hi> with a Letter.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petruchio,</hi> my Lord, <hi>Piſanoes</hi> Secretary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>But <hi>Lorenzo</hi>'s Engine a very knave.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>My very good Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>What's here? It can be no goodneſs.</p>
                  <stage>Reads,</stage>
                  <p>My Lord, I would not have you go to Bed to night, he won't let me ſleep now, I dreamt as much, ſomething will be done to give <hi>Florence</hi> liberty: In the depth of night you may cunningly diſperſe ſome rumours in the City, that the Duke is dead, the people muſt be diſtracted, in the common fright be not you wanting in your Perſon to aſſiſt their fears, and ſpeak well of <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> ſpeak well of the Divel: My humble ſervice to your Lord, and ſay he has power to command me in all things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>My Very good Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>No matter and you were both hang'd; <hi>Rogero,</hi> ſhe him the Wine-ſellar: Let me ſee, I muſt report the Duke's death, I can't abide this word Death, yet he deſires me but to report it; hum, if it be falſe? why ſo much the better; there will be the leſs harm in't; if it ſhould prove true, they will believe me another time: Well, I will drink my ſelf half drunk, and be fortified.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:101820:15"/>Enter Duke, <hi>Amidea, Lorenzo, Sciarrha, Florio,</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> you exceed in Entertainment,</l>
                     <l>Banquet our Eyes too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>He will feaſt all Senſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Only a toy, my Lord, I cannot call't</l>
                     <l>A Mask, not worthy of this preſence, yet</l>
                     <l>It ſpeaks the freedom of my Heart, and gratitude</l>
                     <l>For this great honour.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amidea</hi> muſt ſit near us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lords your places, 't wo' not be</l>
                     <l>Worth half this Ceremony, let 'em begin.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Luſt,</hi> richly apparrel'd, the Pleaſures attending.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Who's the Preſenter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luſt,</hi> Sir, pray obſerve.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Luſt.</hi> Now let <hi>Luſt</hi> poſſeſs the Throne</l>
                     <l>Of Love, and rule in Hearts alone:</l>
                     <l>Tou ſweet Tempters to my Sin,</l>
                     <l>Beauty, Smiles, and Kiſſes win</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon frail Mortals, let them know</l>
                     <l>There is no Happineſs, but you</l>
                     <l>Shoot no Arrows tipp'd with Lead,</l>
                     <l>Each Shaft hath his golden head:</l>
                     <l>Call no Love, delude Men ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Through the Fleſh, the Spirits kill,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſpend all your <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Art to take</l>
                     <l>Common Perſons, Greatneſs make</l>
                     <l>By your potent Charms to be</l>
                     <l>Subjects unto Hell and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> me,</l>
                     <l>Inflame but Kings with looſe deſire,</l>
                     <l>Ye ſoon ſet all the World on fire.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a young Man in rich Habit and Crown'd.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>What's he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A wild young Man that follows Luſt,</l>
                     <l>He has too much Blood it ſeems.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Why looks he back?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There is a thing call'd Death that follows him</l>
                     <l>With a large train of Furies.</l>
                     <l>Hang his Conſcience, it whines too much.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>This is too plain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He does not tremble yet,</l>
                     <stage>Aſide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </stage>
                     <l>By-an-by, Sir, you ſhall ſee all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Tormentors</l>
                     <l>Join with 'em, there's the ſport on't<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:101820:16"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Methinks they</l>
                     <l>Should have been firſt for th' antimask.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh no!</l>
                     <l>In Hell they do not ſtand upon the method,</l>
                     <l>As we at Court,</l>
                     <l>Siſter you do ill,</l>
                     <l>To keep the Duke in talk, he cannot ſee</l>
                     <l>The Divel for you</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>The Furies join in the Dance, and in the end, carry the young Man away.</stage>
                  <p>How does your Highneſs like this dance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My eyes ſo feaſted here, I did not mind it,</l>
                     <l>But I preſume 'twas handſome.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh the Lethargy</l>
                     <l>Of Princes! we ha' kept you, Sir, from bed:</l>
                     <l>More lights.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Good night to all, to you the beſt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha</hi> bind us ever by performance.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>We are all yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And <hi>Florence</hi> thine, once more—</l>
                     <l>Brighteſt of Ladies.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You are firm.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Suſpect not.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt all, but <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> and <hi>Florio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I do not like my Brother's Moral-Mask,</l>
                     <l>The Duke himſelf was perſonated, I</l>
                     <l>Wonder it did not ſtartle him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I hope</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha</hi> does not mean ſo ill as that</l>
                     <l>Did promiſe, he's return'd, his looks are full</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Sciarrha.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Of threatning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amidea,</hi> go not to bed,</l>
                     <l>And yet no matter, I can do't alone:</l>
                     <l>Take both your reſt, and in your Prayers commend</l>
                     <l>The Duke to Heaven, 'tis Charity, h'as made</l>
                     <l>His Will already, and bequeath'd his Body</l>
                     <l>To you, Siſter, pity his Soul for't, 'tis now</l>
                     <l>Within few Minutes of departing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why this way I muſt help him in his Groans</l>
                     <l>To bring his fleſh a-bed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>You wo'not kill him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not of your mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>I know you cannot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101820:16"/>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You are not ſtudied ſo perfect in</l>
                     <l>His deſtiny, I hope, I will endeavour—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>To kill your Prince?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>What, here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>No, in his Chamber.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Shall it be read in Stories of our <hi>Florence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha</hi> firſt did ſtain his Family</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a Treaſon?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Was he not invited?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, by his Luſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And in your crowned Tables,</l>
                     <l>And Hoſpitality will you murder him?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes, and the reaſon wherefore he was murder'd,</l>
                     <l>Shall juſtifie the Deed to all Poſterity,</l>
                     <l>He came to wrong my Siſter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wanton heat,</l>
                     <l>Let youthful Blood excuſe him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>So it muſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Miſtake me not, oh think but who he is,</l>
                     <l>The Duke, that word muſt needs awake your piety<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How will good Men in this remembrance</l>
                     <l>Abhor your Cruelty, that ſend to hell</l>
                     <l>One with the weight of all his Sins upon him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is too late to cool with Argument</l>
                     <l>My incenſed Blood; will you go dally with him?</l>
                     <l>I ha' gone</l>
                     <l>So far in promiſe, if you claſp not with him,</l>
                     <l>It will be dangerous if he out-live</l>
                     <l>This night.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>I ha' thought on't, ſend him to my Bed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do not queſtion what I purpoſe, Heaven</l>
                     <l>Witneſs to my chaſte thoughts.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Wo't thou truſt him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I will do much, Sir, to preſerve his life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And your innocence: Be not you ſuſpectful,</l>
                     <l>At the worſt, you can but reſpite your Revenge.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Doſt thou not fear unhappy <hi>Lucrece</hi> chance,</l>
                     <l>Or wretched <hi>Philomel</hi>'s diſhonour?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No.</l>
                     <l>Give me his life, and ſend your Wanton to me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'le to my Chamber, fear me not <hi>Sciarrha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Have not one thought ſo bad, I ſha' not proſper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Virgins in Heaven will ſuffer with me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit <hi>Ami. &amp; Flo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Truſt her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101820:17"/>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis but deferring of my Juſtice.</l>
                     <l>She wo'not kill him ſure: draw on her Soul</l>
                     <l>The guilt ſhe hates in mine, if ſhe do yield</l>
                     <l>To the hot encounter: Ha? 'twill be juſt,</l>
                     <l>That both their Hearts weep Blood, to purge their Luſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Florio</hi> and <hi>Amidea.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>My Ponyard?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I've no black Intent</l>
                     <l>To ſtain't with any Blood.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Take it, I know, thou art my virtuous Siſter.</l>
                     <l>It were wickedneſs to doubt thy purpoſe,</l>
                     <l>Or the event.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Now leave me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſt a Guard of Angels.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>They are coming.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Enter <hi>Sciarrlia</hi> and Duke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Look, there ſhe is, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Deareſt <hi>Sciarrha.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To your recreation, here</l>
                     <l>I'le obſcure my ſelf, <hi>Florio?</hi> 'tis well.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Withdraws behind the Scenes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Lady, you know me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, my Prince.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I was ſo,</l>
                     <l>Till I ſaw thee, but I gave up that Title,</l>
                     <l>A conqueſt to thy Beauty, which among</l>
                     <l>Her other Wonders hath created me</l>
                     <l>A Subject and Servant, and I ſhall</l>
                     <l>Be happier to be receiv'd yours by</l>
                     <l>One of thoſe Names, than Duke of <hi>Tuſcany.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh! take your ſelf agen, uſe your Greatneſs</l>
                     <l>To make the hearts of <hi>Florence</hi> bow to you,</l>
                     <l>And pay their Duties thus.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Riſe <hi>Amidea,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſince you have given my Power back, it will</l>
                     <l>Become me to command.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>And me to obey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſee thy noble Brother hath bin faithful</l>
                     <l>To my deſires, he has prepar'd thee with</l>
                     <l>A Story of my Love, which thou reward'ſt</l>
                     <l>With too much humbleneſs: I could dwell ever</l>
                     <l>Here, and imagine I am in a Temple,</l>
                     <l>To offer on this Altar of thy Lip,</l>
                     <stage>[Kiſſes her often.</stage>
                     <l>Myriads of flaming Kiſſes with a Cloud</l>
                     <l>Of Sighs breath'd from from my heart,</l>
                     <l>Which by the Oblation would increaſe his Stock,</l>
                     <l>To make my Pay eternal.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>What mean you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101820:17"/>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That Queſtion is propounded timely: Hadſt</l>
                     <l>Not interrupted me, I ſhould ha' loſt</l>
                     <l>My ſelf upon thy Lips, and quite forgot</l>
                     <l>There is a Bliſs beyond it.</l>
                     <l>Transform me there to Happineſs;</l>
                     <l>I'll laugh at all the Fables of the Gods,</l>
                     <l>And teach our Poets, after I know thee,</l>
                     <l>To write the true <hi>Elizium.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Good my Lord:</l>
                     <l>I underſtand you not, and yet I fear</l>
                     <l>You do not mean well, if you have brought with you</l>
                     <l>A ſinful Purpoſe, which I may ſuſpect.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why, Madam, what do you imagine I</l>
                     <l>Came hither for?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How! Is't come to that?</l>
                     <l>Your Brother gave you more</l>
                     <l>Deſirous of the Sport, and brought me hither</l>
                     <l>Ripe for your Dalliance: Did you not expect me?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>And to what other purpoſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>To tell you that you are not virtuous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm of your mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But I am not ſo wicked,</l>
                     <l>To be of yours: Oh, think but who you are;</l>
                     <l>Your Title ſpeaks you neareſt Heaven, and points</l>
                     <l>You out a glorious Reign among the Angels:</l>
                     <l>Do not depoſe your ſelf of one, and be</l>
                     <l>Of the other diſ-inherited.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I would</l>
                     <l>Your Brother heard you: Prithee, do not waſte</l>
                     <l>This tedious Divinity; I am</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd to grapple with you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Keep off.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Shews the Ponyard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
                  <p>Turn'd <hi>Amazon!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Prince, come not too near me;</l>
                     <l>For, By my Honour, ſince you have loſt your own,</l>
                     <l>Although I bow in Duty to your Perſon,</l>
                     <l>I hate your black Thoughts. Tempt not my juſt Hand</l>
                     <l>With violent Approach: I dare, and will</l>
                     <l>Do that will grieve you, if you have a Soul.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou dar'ſt not kill me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>True: But I dare die.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Be thy own Murtherer!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101820:18"/>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Rather than you ſhould be my Raviſher.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou canſt not be ſo mercileſs; 'tis leſs Sin</l>
                     <l>To be unchaſte. I am thy Prince, I prithee</l>
                     <l>Throw by that cruel Weapon; let our War</l>
                     <l>Be ſoft Embraces, ſhooting amorous Smiles;</l>
                     <l>Kill and reſtore each other with a Kiſs.</l>
                     <l>I know thou canſt not be unkind ſo long:</l>
                     <l>Then I command thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I muſt not obey</l>
                     <l>To be your Strumpet: Though my Hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be unskilful,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall ſoon find my Heart</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll not believe—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>She wounds her Arm</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let this deſerve your Faith, I dare be juſt:</l>
                     <l>This Crimſon River iſſuing from my Arm.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Never: It ſhall flow; and if this Chanel</l>
                     <l>Yield not enough, I'll ſtrike another Vein;</l>
                     <l>And after that, another, and not pity</l>
                     <l>The murmuring Stream, till through a prodigal Wound</l>
                     <l>I have drain'd the Fountain. This doth weep for you,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall extol my Death, if it may teach</l>
                     <l>You to correct your Blood.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There's ſo much gone</l>
                     <l>From me, I cool apace: This Action</l>
                     <l>Hath ſhot an Ague through me. <hi>Amidea,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pity thy ſelf.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not till you ſwear Repentance:</l>
                     <l>I do not faint yet, 'tis ſomewhat about;</l>
                     <l>But I can find a nearer way: This does it.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Contain, I am ſorry, ſorry from my Soul.</l>
                     <l>Truſt me, I do bleed inward, <hi>Amidea,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can anſwer all thy Drops. Oh, pardon me:</l>
                     <l>Thou faint'ſt already; Doſt not?</l>
                     <l>Look to thy Wound.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>May I believe you, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I dare not think awry: Again I ask</l>
                     <l>Forgiveneſs. In thy Innocence I ſee</l>
                     <l>My own Deformity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> haſtily embraceth <hi>Amidea.</hi> Enter <hi>Florio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now a thouſand Bleſſings</l>
                     <l>Reward thy Goodneſs; thou deſerv'ſt a Statue,</l>
                     <l>A tall one. But apply</l>
                     <l>Betimes unto thy Wound. <hi>Florio,</hi> aſſiſt her.</l>
                     <l>And now, my Lord—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>[<hi>Ex.</hi> Am. <hi>&amp;</hi> Flo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:101820:18"/>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> I'll begin to be thy Lord:</l>
                     <l>I brought Intentions of Diſhonour to thee,</l>
                     <l>And thy fair Siſter; but I am reconcil'd</l>
                     <l>To Virtue, and will ſtudy how to ſatisfie</l>
                     <l>For you and <hi>Florence.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You will be more precious,</l>
                     <l>Than had you never fallen: I am all Joy</l>
                     <l>In your Converſion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Is <hi>Lorenzo</hi> a-bed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lorenzo!</hi> I think he has not ſaid his Prayers yet:</l>
                     <l>But—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>What!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot tell; may be he does not uſe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord, you now are lovely;</l>
                     <l>'Twere better you'd forget him, he's not right</l>
                     <l>At Heart, I fear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Fear nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To be plain,</l>
                     <l>You cheriſh your Diſeaſe in him, and are</l>
                     <l>Not ſafe while he is near you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not envy him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then I muſt tell you, Sir, he is a Traytor,</l>
                     <l>Within my Knowledge, hath conſpir'd your Death.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>With whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With me: I ſhould ha' kill'd you, Sir,</l>
                     <l>This Night; and every Minute he expects</l>
                     <l>To hear you number'd with the Dead: I can</l>
                     <l>Demonſtrate this: Your Pardon: But, in truth,</l>
                     <l>The Injuries you meant us, were ſevere;</l>
                     <l>And he, with as much Violence, did urge 'em</l>
                     <l>To your Deſtruction. But your Piety</l>
                     <l>Hath charm'd my Purpoſe, and I look upon you</l>
                     <l>With new Obedience.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Enter <hi>Florio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Poſſible!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We wo' not ſhift the Scene, till you believe it.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Florio,</hi> intreat my Lord <hi>Lorenzo</hi> hither:</l>
                     <l>Step but behind the Arras, and your Ear</l>
                     <l>Shall tell you who's the greateſt Traytor living.</l>
                     <l>Obſerve but when I tell him, you are ſlain;</l>
                     <l>How he'll rejoice, and call me <hi>Florence</hi> great</l>
                     <l>Preſerver; bleſs my Arm, that in your Blood</l>
                     <l>Hath given our groaning State a Liberty.</l>
                     <l>Then truſt <hi>Sciarrha.</hi> But, obſerve; I hear him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Whom talk'd he to?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soi.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis done—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>What? Good <hi>Sciarrha?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soi.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> is dead.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101820:19"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We are not left ſo miſerable,</l>
                     <l>Heaven is more kind to <hi>Florence.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With this Hand</l>
                     <l>I made a Paſſage for his Soul.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Defend,</l>
                     <l>Omnipotence! What, murder'd! And by noble</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha!</hi> How my Ear abuſes me!</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Did not we plot it too?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How? We<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Collect:</l>
                     <l>I fear you are not well. Pray, tell me why</l>
                     <l>You talk thus? Where's the <hi>Duke?</hi> He hath a Guard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>An Army of Heaven about him. Who in <hi>Florence</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Dares be ſo black a Devil, to attempt</l>
                     <l>His Death?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This is fine Cunning. Why, that Devil is</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> if he dares deny it: We are in private,</l>
                     <l>You need appear no Stranger to that's done</l>
                     <l>By your Direction.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I in the Practice!</l>
                     <l>Then let me creep into the Earth, and riſe</l>
                     <l>A Monſter to affright Mankind. <hi>Sciarrha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I muſt abhor thee for it. Oh, my Prince!</l>
                     <l>My deareſt Kinſman! May thy Hand rot off.</l>
                     <l>Treaſon, Treaſon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then my Sword ſhall fetch</l>
                     <l>Another Witneſs in thy Heart.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>As they draw, the <hi>Duke</hi> interpoſes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Royal Lord! Nay, let him kill me now:</l>
                     <l>I've ſo much Joy and Peace about me, 'twere</l>
                     <l>A Sin to wiſh my Life beyond this Minute.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Put up, I ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord, we are both cozen'd:</l>
                     <l>That very Smile's a Traytor.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come, be calm:</l>
                     <l>You are too paſſionate, <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> and Miſtook <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But I hold him noble:</l>
                     <l>I ſee he made this Trial of my Faith,</l>
                     <l>And I forgive him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye ſhall be Friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you ſhall, I ſa</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Coſmo</hi> and <hi>Alonzo</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Duke!</hi>—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                  <p>Where's the <hi>Duke?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord, we are bleſs'd to ſee you ſafe: Report</l>
                     <l>Hath frighted all the City with your Death:</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:101820:19"/>
                     <l>People forſake their Beds, and ſeeking how</l>
                     <l>To be inform'd, increaſe the wretched Tumult.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There's nothing but Confuſion: All Men tremble,</l>
                     <l>As if ſome general Fire invaded <hi>Florence.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Have Comfort, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>What's to be done?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Depazzi</hi> has remembred,</l>
                     <l>My Lord, there is no Safety for the State,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs you perſonally appeaſe 'em.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope they'll tear him: Would he were dead any way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                  <p>He hath counſell'd well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Preſence only hath the power to charm 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I fear their Rage: Where is our Guard?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alonzo,</hi> haſte afore, proclaim Our Pardon,</l>
                     <l>And that We live to give the Offenders Mercy.</l>
                     <l>Why are We born to Greatneſs, mock'd with State,</l>
                     <l>When every Tumult ſtaggers Our proud Fate?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Quarrel is deferr'd, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S Quartus.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY Plots thrive not, my Engines all deceive me.</l>
                     <l>Are there</l>
                     <l>No faithful Villains left in Nature? All</l>
                     <l>Turn'd honeſt! Man nor Spirit aid <hi>Lorenzo!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who hath not Patience to expect his Fate,</l>
                     <l>But muſt compel it! How <hi>Sciarrha</hi> play'd</l>
                     <l>The Dog-bolt wo' me! And had not I provided</l>
                     <l>In Wiſdom for him, that Diſtreſs had ruin'd me.</l>
                     <l>His frozen Siſter <hi>Amidea</hi> too</l>
                     <l>Hath half converted him; but I muſt ſet</l>
                     <l>New Wheels in motion, to make him yet</l>
                     <l>More hateful, and then cut him from his Stalk,</l>
                     <l>Ripe for my Vengeance: I'll not truſt the Rabble.</l>
                     <l>Confuſion on the giddy Multitude,</l>
                     <l>That but two Minutes e'er the <hi>Duke</hi> came at 'em,</l>
                     <l>Bellow'd out Liberty, ſhook the City with</l>
                     <l>Their Throats; no ſooner ſaw him, but they melted</l>
                     <l>With the hot Apprehenſion of a Gallows.</l>
                     <l>Sudden Rot</l>
                     <l>Conſume this baſe Herd: And the Devil want</l>
                     <l>Any Cattle for his own Teeth, theſe are for him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Enter a Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:101820:20"/>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> my Lord deſires to ſpeak with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha!</hi> Come near—you underſtand; admit him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Ex. <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Welcome, my noble Lord;</l>
                     <stage>[Enter <hi>Sciarrha</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>You were not wont to viſit me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor mean ever to do't again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You bring Frowns.</p>
                  <p>I can be fullen too—What is your pleaſure?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sc.</speaker>
                  <p>You have abus'd me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You have injur'd me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>In what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Betray'd me baſely to the <hi>Duke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>You deny'd then you were a Traytor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes: I was no Fool, to run my Neck upon</l>
                     <l>The Axe, and give you ſuch a Cauſe of Triumph<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Were it again in queſtion—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Y'are a Villain, Sir;</l>
                     <l>And I muſt have it certified under your own Hand.</l>
                     <l>To ſhew the Duke.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You ſhall be humbled to</l>
                     <l>Confeſs the contrary; nay, ſubſcribe</l>
                     <l>That I am honeſt, and deſire my Pardon.</l>
                     <l>Look, I have a Sword, and Arm, and Vigour;</l>
                     <l>Dare fight with thee, didſt ride upon a Whirl-wind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Provoke the on a Rock, in Waves, in Fire;</l>
                     <l>And kill thee without Scruple: Such a Strength</l>
                     <l>Is Innocence.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Innocence! Doſt not fear a Thunder-bolt?</l>
                     <l>I ſhall be charitable to the World, and I</l>
                     <l>Cut thee in pieces.</l>
                     <l>Didſt not thou rail upon the <hi>Duke?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I grant it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Call him a Tyrant?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>More I do confeſs;</l>
                     <l>I did exaſperate you to kill or murder him;</l>
                     <l>Give it what Name you pleaſe: With Joy I brought him,</l>
                     <l>Under the colour of your Gueſt, to be</l>
                     <l>The common Sacrifice. All this I remember.</l>
                     <l>But is Heaven's Stock of Mercy ſpent already,</l>
                     <l>That Sins, though great and horrid, may not be</l>
                     <l>Forgiven to the Heart that groans with Penitence?</l>
                     <l>Are the Eternal Fountains quite ſeal'd up?</l>
                     <l>I was a Villain, Traytor, Murderer,</l>
                     <l>In my Conſenting to his Death; but hope</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Stains are now waſh'd off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Haſt thou repented?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Truſt me, I have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>The Devil is turn'd religious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As he was</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101820:20"/>
                     <l>A luſtful Duke, a Tyrant, I had loſt him:</l>
                     <l>In his Return to Piety: He commanded</l>
                     <l>My Prayers, and freſh Obedience to wait on him.</l>
                     <l>He's now my Prince again.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>This is but Cunning, to ſave your Life.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter divers Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen arm'd.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>My Life! Within there, ha? Welcome.</p>
                  <p>1. My gracious Lord.</p>
                  <p>2. Wil't pleaſe your Honour,</p>
                  <p>Command my Service?</p>
                  <p>3. Or me?</p>
                  <p>4. Or any?</p>
                  <p>5. Our Swords and Lives are yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Perhaps your Lordſhip hath ſome Buſineſs</l>
                     <l>With theſe Gentlemen: I'll take ſome other time.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By no means, good <hi>Sciarrha:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You viſit ſeldom, thoſe are daily with me;</l>
                     <l>Men that expect Employment, that wear Swords,</l>
                     <l>And carry Spirits, both to be engag'd,</l>
                     <l>If I but name a Cauſe. Gentlemen, Draw.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>My Providence has betray'd me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now, <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> you that with ſingle Valour dare come home</l>
                     <l>To affront me thus; Know, but too late, thy Heart</l>
                     <l>Is at the Mercy of my Breath; theſe Swords</l>
                     <l>Can fetch it when I pleaſe; and to prevent</l>
                     <l>Your Boaſt of this great Daring: I beſeech,</l>
                     <l>As you do love and honour your <hi>Lorenzo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No Hand advance a Weapon; ſheath again,</l>
                     <l>And leave us: I owe Service to your Loves,</l>
                     <l>But muſt not ſo diſhonour you.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All Gentl.</hi> We obey.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Exeunt Gentlemen.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>They're gone: This is ſome Nobleneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You ſee</l>
                     <l>I do not fear your Sword, alone I have</l>
                     <l>Too much Advantage; yet you may imagine</l>
                     <l>How eaſily I could correct this Raſhneſs:</l>
                     <l>But in my Fear to offend gracious Heaven</l>
                     <l>With a new Crime, having ſo late obtain'd</l>
                     <l>My Peace, I give you Freedom.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Do I dream?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pray, chide me ſtill; I will be patient</l>
                     <l>To hear my Shame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is this to be believ'd?</l>
                     <l>Doth not <hi>Lorenzo</hi> counterfeit this Vertue?</l>
                     <l>He does: It is impoſſible he ſhould repent.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:101820:21"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why, tell me, <hi>Sciarrha;</hi> and let us argue a while</l>
                     <l>In cooler Blood. Did not you once reſolve</l>
                     <l>To kill the <hi>Duke</hi> too?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To give him Death with your own Hand?</l>
                     <l>Methinks it ſhould be the ſame Parricide</l>
                     <l>In you, if not a greater; yet you chang'd</l>
                     <l>Your purpoſe. Why did you not go through,</l>
                     <l>And murder him?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>He was converted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Good: That taught you Mercy, and perhaps Repentance For your Intent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>It did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why ſhould not, Sir,</l>
                     <l>The ſame Converſion of the <hi>Duke</hi> poſſeſs</l>
                     <l>My Heart with as much Piety to him,</l>
                     <l>And Sorrow for my ſelf? If I ſhould ſay,</l>
                     <l>You are but cunning; is this Shape of Honeſty?</l>
                     <l>And ſtill ſuſpect your Soul to be a Traytor?</l>
                     <l>Might you not blame my Want of Charity?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He ſays but right: We are</l>
                     <l>Both Men, frail things: 'Tis not impoſſible.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am reconcil'd to Heaven already, and the Duke: If you</l>
                     <l>Be ſtill unſatisfi'd, I am ready, Sir.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Circumſtance conſider'd, I incline</l>
                     <l>To think this may be honeſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come, <hi>Schiarrha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We are both haſty:</l>
                     <l>My Nature is corrected at this Minute:</l>
                     <l>I'm Friends with all the World; but in your Love</l>
                     <l>Shall number many Bleſſings.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>I am converted.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Petruchio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>What's the News?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord <hi>Depazzi</hi> prays ſome Conference</l>
                     <l>In the next Chamber: We arriv'd by chance</l>
                     <l>Together at your Gate: I do not like his Talk, Sir.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hang him, Property, let him</l>
                     <l>Expect; thou art come i'the Opportunity:</l>
                     <l>I could have wiſh'd—Be wiſe, and ſecond me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He waits upon <hi>Piſano,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe Health I may enquire; I ha' not ſeen him</l>
                     <l>Since he departed ſick: A fit Occaſion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Married to <hi>Oriana!</hi> Thou miſtak'ſt:</l>
                     <l>'Tis <hi>Amidea,</hi> Lord <hi>Sciarrha</hi>'s Siſter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That Contract's broken, and the old Lady</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:101820:21"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Morroſſa</hi> is violent to have the Marriage</l>
                     <l>Finiſhed with her Daughter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is't true, <hi>Piſano</hi> marrries <hi>Oriana,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The rich <hi>Morroſſa</hi>'s Daughter?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We did expect to hear your Siſter ſhould</l>
                     <l>Have been his Bride: Has he forſaken <hi>Amidea?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not you ſerve <hi>Piſano?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And dare you talk he's to be married</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Oriana?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If they live 'till to Morrow:</l>
                     <l>There's great Proviſion to my knowledg, and—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Take that, and learn to ſpeak a Truth hereafter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That Blow, ſhall coſt his Life,</l>
                     <l>It is not poſſible he dares affront</l>
                     <l>You thus; the World takes notice of a Contract.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am not to give</l>
                     <l>Account for my Lord's Actions, let him anſwer</l>
                     <l>And juſtifie his Honour: But, my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Since I am provoked, I muſt declare he has</l>
                     <l>Call'd back his Vows to <hi>Amidea,</hi> given</l>
                     <l>Her freedom, and does mean to uſe his own,</l>
                     <l>And this he dares publiſh.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>What, diſclaim'd a Lady of her Birth and glorious Merit!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Th'art a Villain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Lord, he is not worth your Anger, he</l>
                     <l>Declares but what his Maſter hath committed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis none of his Fault.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It becomes my Duty</l>
                     <l>To take Correction, my Lord, from you.</l>
                     <l>I am a Servant, a poor Gentleman.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I ſuſpect the Circumſtance at his departure?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſtrange you knew not this before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt examine, if he dares—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Be patient.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Teach Fools and Children patience,</l>
                     <l>The dogs eat up <hi>Sciarrha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If <hi>Piſano</hi> out-lives my Siſter's Wrongs.</l>
                     <l>Falſe Heaven, why ſhould thy Altars ſave?</l>
                     <l>'Tis juſt that <hi>Hymen</hi> light him to his Grave.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Farewel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> dull paſſionate Fool,</l>
                     <l>Kill <hi>Piſano,</hi> and be loſt thy ſelf; or if his Sword</l>
                     <l>Conclude thy Life, both ways I am reveng'd.</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101820:22"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Petruchio,</hi> thou didſt hit my Inſtructions rarely,</l>
                     <l>And I applaud thee: Now ſend in <hi>Depazzi,</hi> and viſit me anon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Depazzi</hi> and <hi>Rogero.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I would ſpeak a Word or two in private<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You may.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Is no body within hearing? All clear behind the Arras?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Make no doubt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, the truth is, I am very fearful: Is your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſure there are no Eves-droppers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>What needs this Circumſtance? I pray come to the point.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis not unknown to your Lordſhip, that you have bin my very good Lord, neither am I ignorant, that I am your humble Servant; you advanc'd me, brought me into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Nobles, and I brought you a reaſonable number of Crowns: I am not the firſt wiſe Citizen that hath bin conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into a fooliſh Courtier: But, my Lord, I beſeech you par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me: It will out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>What's the Matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ready to burſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>With what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Treaſon, Treaſon, now <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ts out, and I feel my Body the lighter for't already: The laſt Plot did not take, you ſee, and I would humbly intreat your Lordſhip to excuſe me, and get ſome body elſe hereafter to be your Traytor in my ſtead.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>If you did but know the tenderneſs of my Conſtitution, or feel the Pangs and Convulſions that I ſuffer, you would pity me: I fall away, you ſee, I cannot ſleep for dreaming of an Ax, I have caus'd my hangings of <hi>Holofernes</hi> to be taken down in my Dining-room, becauſe I dare not look upon a Head that is cut off in it, ſomething of my Complexion: My Wiſdom tells me, I am a fool to be ſo fearful, but my Conſcience tells me, I am a greater fool, if I ha' not Wit enough in my Pate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to keep my Head on my Shoulders. I beſeech your Lordſhip, take me into your conſideration, I am but a mortal, though I be a Lord; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man hath not the like Gift of Impudence, I have a weak Stomach, and Treaſon is Phyſick to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You wo' not betray me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>But, alas! in ſuch a Caſe, I may ſoon bewray my ſelf, and then your Lordſhip may ſoon be ſmelt out: To prevent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome miſchief that may happen, I deſire to leave off, while I am well, and that your Lordſhip may know I mean plainly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:101820:22"/>
I ha' brought you all your Letters, I durſt not truſt any other place with 'em for fear of State-Rats. I have unript my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to you, and there they are to a Tittle—now I may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſwear, I have no hand with your Lordſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>This is very ſtrange.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Miſtake not, my good Lord, I am ſtill your Creature, but I have a great mind to be honeſt a little while, among the weaker ſort of Nobility: Yet thus much perſwade your ſelf, I will ne'er wrong your Lordſhip in a Syllable; ſhould you tell me of a thouſand Treaſons and Stratagems, I will never reveal any, I ſcorn that; but your Lordſhip muſt pardon me, I will be a Traitor no longer, that's certain; I will be honeſt, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe no Body ſhall hit me in the teeth after I am dead, and ſay, look where <hi>Depazzi</hi> carries his head very high; and, my Lord, the more to induce your Lordſhip to diſmiſs me—<hi>Rogero.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Give me the Gold. I have brought 1500 Crowns more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>That I may have my Lordſhips good Will, to leave my Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice before it be taken from me, and preferr'd to a worſe, 'tis half the price I paid for't. I love Peace and a little Honeſty. I know your Honour will find an able Man for it, and it is fit I ſhould pay for my <hi>Quietas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>And what do you reſolve?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>To return to the Dunghill from whence I came, for though I was born in the City, I have ſome Land in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, durty Acres and Manſion-houſe, where I will be the Miracle of a Courtier, and keep good Hoſpitality, love my Neighbours, and their Wives, and conſequently get their Children, be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd amongſt the Juſtices, ſleep upon every Bench, keep a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in my own Houſe to be my Idolater, and furniſh me with Jeſts; and when I have nothing elſe to do, I will think of the Court, and how much I have bin oblig'd to your Lordſhip: My Lord, I may do you Service with a leading Voice in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the Kennel will cry a'my Side; if it come to Election, you or your Friend ſhall carry it, againſt the Common-wealth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Sir, ſince you have expreſs'd your ſelf ſo freely, I will not counſel you againſt your Diſpoſition to ſtay at Court, you may go when, and whither you pleaſe; and though at par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I have nothing worth your Acceptation, I will beſtow theſe Crowns upon your Servant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt give 'em me agen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:101820:23"/>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, my Lord, I love a little Honeſty, 'tis his Lordſhip's</p>
                  <l>Bounty, it will be a Stock to ſet me up, for my ſelf at Court,</l>
                  <l>when your Lordſhip is retir'd into the Country, I humbly thank</l>
                  <l>your Lordſhip, and take my leave of yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>The Duke my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit, Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>How the Duke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Signior</hi> Depazzi.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He has bin earneſt with me, and pleaſe your Highneſs,</l>
                     <l>To be his humble Suitor, he may have</l>
                     <l>Freedom to leave the Court.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſhall be baniſht.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>What time will your Grace allow to provide?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Two hours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I had rather loſe my Head at home, and ſave Charges</l>
                     <l>Of Travail, I beſeech your Grace.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, 'tis granted, let him not trouble us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Enjoy the Country, and return when the Duke ſends for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dep.</speaker>
                  <p>I humbly thank his Highneſs, and will pray for your in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſe of Grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> are we private?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>I am very melancholy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I know the cauſe, 'tis <hi>Amidea.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not wiſh her dead.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>It were a Sin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not in Heaven, Sir; yet</l>
                     <l>There be Ladies, that would think it a promotion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It were pity ſhe ſhould leave</l>
                     <l>The World, till ſhe hath taught by her Example</l>
                     <l>The neareſt way.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I am very confident ſhe's yet honeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet, <hi>Lorenzo?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ay, Sir, but I'me not of Opinion it is</l>
                     <l>Impoſſible to know a change.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Take heed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I muſt confeſs, ſhe has been very valiant,</l>
                     <l>In making you remove your Siege, and ſhew'd</l>
                     <l>Prety dexterity at the Ponyard,</l>
                     <l>See her ſelf bleed:</l>
                     <l>You were ſtartled</l>
                     <l>To ſee her ſtrike her Arm, and grew compaſſionate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I was not Marble; we break Adamant</l>
                     <l>With blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and could I be a Man, and not</l>
                     <l>Be mov'd to ſee that haſty Ebb of Life</l>
                     <l>For my ſake?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aſcend agen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And fix in your lov'd Orb, he brings this comfort</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:101820:23"/>
                     <l>That can aſſure it.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall enjoy her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Enjoy fair <hi>Amidea?</hi> do not tempt,</l>
                     <l>Or rather mock my frailty with ſuch a promiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Shake off your melancholly ſlumber, I</l>
                     <l>Have here decreed you ſhall poſſeſs her.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Is this in nature?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus: <hi>Sciarrha's</hi> Life</l>
                     <l>And Fortunes are already growing forfeit,</l>
                     <l>Theſe brains have Plotted ſo; your mercy ſhall</l>
                     <l>Purchaſe what you can wiſh.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do this,</l>
                     <l>And I'll repent the folly of my penitence,</l>
                     <l>And take thee to my Soul, a nearer pledge</l>
                     <l>Than Blood or Nature gave me: I'm renew'd,</l>
                     <l>I feel my natural warmth return, when, where,</l>
                     <l>Is this to be expected? I grow Old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>While our Embraces are deferr'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I go, to haſten your delight,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha's</hi> Fate is caſt</l>
                     <l>Firmer than Deſtiny.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art my Prophet, I'll raiſe thee up an Altar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Truſt theſe brains.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou mak'ſt my Spirit caper in my veins.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Coſmo, <hi>and two Gentlemen above.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>This way they paſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I would not ſee 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Why?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What melancholy o'th' ſuddain? It is now paſt cure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know it is, and therefore do not</l>
                     <l>Deſire to Witneſs their Solemnity, ſhould <hi>Oriana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>See me to day.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I fear ſhe'd be diſpleas'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>We diſpute not thoſe nice formalities.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Alonzo, Piero, Piſano, Oriana, Moroſſa.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>She has ſpied you already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſorry for't.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Oriana <hi>faints.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <p>How is't, my Child?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>She faints, what grief is ſo unmannerly</l>
                     <l>To interrupt thee now, <hi>Oriana?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <p>Daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Will Heaven divorce us e'er the Prieſt have made</l>
                     <l>Our Marriage perfect? She returns.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:101820:24"/>
                  <speaker>Oria.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why were you ſo unkind to call me from</l>
                     <l>A pleaſing ſlumber? Death has a fine dwelling.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This ſhews her heart's not yet conſenting; 'tis</l>
                     <l>Her Mother's fierce command.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>Something ſpake to me from that Window.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>There is nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Set forward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I do not like this Interruption; 'Tis</l>
                     <l>Ominous.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Amidea.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not for my ſake, but your own, go back,</l>
                     <l>Or take ſome other way; this leads to death.</l>
                     <l>My Brother.—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>What of him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tranſported with</l>
                     <l>The fury of Revenge for my diſhonour,</l>
                     <l>Hath vowed to kill you in your Nuptial Glory.</l>
                     <l>Alas! I fear his haſte: Now, good my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Have mercy on your ſelf; I do not beg</l>
                     <l>Your pity upon me, I know too well</l>
                     <l>You cannot love me now.</l>
                     <l>But again,</l>
                     <l>I would beſeech you, cheriſh your own life,</l>
                     <l>Though I be loſt for ever.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is worth</l>
                     <l>Your care, my Lord.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Alas! her Grief hath made her wild<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> poor Lady!</l>
                     <l>I ſhould not love, <hi>Oriana,</hi> to go back;</l>
                     <l>Set forward, <hi>Amidea,</hi> you may live</l>
                     <l>To be a happier Bride: <hi>Sciarrha</hi> is not</l>
                     <l>So irreligious to prophane theſe Rites.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Will you not then believe me? Pray perſwade him,</l>
                     <l>You are his Freinds. Lady, it will concern</l>
                     <l>You moſt of all indeed: I fear you'll weep</l>
                     <l>To ſee him dead as well as I.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No more,</l>
                     <l>Go forward.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I have done, pray be not angry,</l>
                     <l>That ſtill I wiſh you well, may Heaven divert</l>
                     <l>All harms that threaten you:</l>
                     <l>I hope there is no ſin in this;</l>
                     <l>Indeed I cannot chuſe but pray for you,</l>
                     <l>This might have been my Wedding-day.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:101820:24"/>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Good Heaven!</l>
                     <l>I would it were; my heart can tell, I take</l>
                     <l>No Joy in being his Bride.</l>
                     <l>I will reſign my Place, and wait on you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>If you will marry him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray do not mock me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Amidea,</hi> do not think I mock</l>
                     <l>Your Sorrows; by theſe Tears, that are not worn</l>
                     <l>By every Virgin on her Wedding-day;</l>
                     <l>I am compell'd to give away my ſelf:</l>
                     <l>Your Heart were promis'd, but he ne'er had mine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Am not I wretched too?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Sciarrha, Lorenzo,</hi> aloof with a Guard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sciarrha!</hi> then I propheſie—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Piſano,</hi> where's <hi>Piſano?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here, <hi>Sciarrha.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I ſhould have anſwered with leſs Clamour.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But I would not loſe my Voice, I muſt be heard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And I muſt tell you, 'tis not ſafe to marry.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Why<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Twill be fatal; <hi>Hymen</hi> is gone abroad,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Venus,</hi> Lady of your Nativity,</l>
                     <l>Is found by wiſe Aſtrologers this day</l>
                     <l>I'th' Houſe of Death.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>This muſt not fright me, Sir; ſet forward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>One cold Word, you are a Villain;</l>
                     <l>I do not flatter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am patient:</l>
                     <l>This day I conſecrate to Love, not Anger;</l>
                     <l>We'll meet ſome other time.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Deride my Fury?</l>
                     <l>Then to thy Heart I ſend my own revenge</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Amidea</hi>'s.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Stabs him with a Ponyard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I am murder'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <p>Help, murder Gentlemen, Oh my Unhappineſs!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Lorenzo</hi> with a Guard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Bloody <hi>Sciarrha.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come all at once,</l>
                     <l>Yet let me tell you, my Revenge is perfect,</l>
                     <l>And I would ſpare your Blood, if you deſpiſe</l>
                     <l>My Charity—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No Man attempt his Death;</l>
                     <l>I'll give you Reaſons; this Attempt deſerves</l>
                     <l>An exemplary Juſtice.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:101820:25"/>Enter <hi>Coſmo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am above</l>
                     <l>Your politick reach, and glory in the wound</l>
                     <l>That puniſh'd our Diſhonour: Is he dead?</l>
                     <l>I would not be ſo miſerable, not to ha' ſped him</l>
                     <l>For the Empire.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my Friend, poor <hi>Oriana.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Diſarm him:</l>
                     <l>Return and comfort one another; ſome</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt all but <hi>Lorenzo, Sciar.</hi> and Guards.</stage>
                     <l>Remove <hi>Piſano</hi>'s Body, while I make it</l>
                     <l>My care <hi>Sciarrha</hi> ſcape not.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>None of all give me a ſcratch?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You have forc'd him with diſcretion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Now what muſt I expect?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>You are my Priſoner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>And be confident to find that favour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Favour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be at diſtance,</l>
                     <l>My Lord, I am ſorry for your great Misfortune,</l>
                     <l>And if you can but ſtudy how I may</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſt you, you ſhall ſoon diſcern my love,</l>
                     <l>My readineſs to ſerve you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, this is honeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I will impoſe no more</l>
                     <l>Reſtraint than your own Houſe; you're Honourable:</l>
                     <l>You have many ſevere Enemies: The Duke</l>
                     <l>Look'd graciouſly upon <hi>Piſano,</hi> but—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You ſha'not loſe the ſmalleſt beam of favour,</l>
                     <l>To buy a Man ſo deſperate;</l>
                     <l>I am arm'd to die, and give Example of that Fortitude</l>
                     <l>Shall ſhame the Law's Severity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ha' thought a way</l>
                     <l>To recover you, if you incline to't.</l>
                     <l>Dare you conſent?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To any thing that's noble,</l>
                     <l>Although I never fear'd to ſuffer; I</l>
                     <l>Am not ſo fooliſh to deſpiſe a Life.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There is no difficulty attends it; liſten,</l>
                     <l>The time will not permit much circumſtance:</l>
                     <l>The Duke you know did love your Siſter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Vitiouſly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Her Virtue did but cool him for the preſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>As ſprinklings on a flame, he's now more paſſionate</l>
                     <l>To enjoy her.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:101820:25"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If ſhe conſent to meet</l>
                     <l>His ſoft embrace, with his firſt kiſs he ſeals</l>
                     <l>Your Pardon.</l>
                     <l>The Duke may be ſo taken</l>
                     <l>With her Return to his Delight, who knows</l>
                     <l>But he may marry her, and diſcharge his Dutcheſs</l>
                     <l>With a quaint Sallet: You do apprehend me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And repent more I had one good thought of thee,</l>
                     <l>Than had I kill'd a Thouſand: Save my life</l>
                     <l>And proſtitute my Siſter, though I have</l>
                     <l>No Weapon, I will look thee dead, or breathe</l>
                     <l>A damp ſhall ſtifle thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ha' done,</l>
                     <l>And praiſe your Heathen Reſolution</l>
                     <l>Of Death; go practiſe Immortality,</l>
                     <l>And e'er thy Body hath three Days inhabited</l>
                     <l>A melancholly Chamber in the Earth,</l>
                     <l>This Siſter ſhall be raviſh'd,</l>
                     <l>Mauger thy Duſt and Heraldry.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ha, raviſh'd?</l>
                     <l>When I am dead, was't not ſo? Oh my Soul,</l>
                     <l>I feel it weep within me, and the Tears</l>
                     <l>Soften my Fleſh: <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> I repent my Fury.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I advis'd you the beſt way my Wiſdom could direct.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I thank you for't:</l>
                     <l>You have awak'd my Reaſon; I am aſham'd</l>
                     <l>I was no ſooner ſenſible. Does the Duke</l>
                     <l>Affect my Siſter ſtill, ſay you?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt paſſionately.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>She ſhall obey him then, upon my Life:</l>
                     <l>That's it, my Life; I know ſhe loves me dearly.</l>
                     <l>I ſhall have much ado to win her to it,</l>
                     <l>But ſhe ſhall come, I'll ſend her.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Perform this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I wo'not only ſend her, but prepar'd</l>
                     <l>Not to be diſobedient to his Highneſs:</l>
                     <l>He ſhall command her any thing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do this,</l>
                     <l>And be for ever happy; when theſe have</l>
                     <l>Only for form but waited on you home:</l>
                     <l>This diſingages 'em.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My humbleſt Service</l>
                     <l>To the Duke, I pray; and tell him, <hi>Amidea</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This Night ſhall be at his Diſpoſe, by this.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:101820:26"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm confident, farewell; attend <hi>Sciarrah.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pity the Seaman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that to avoid a ſhelf,</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſtrike upon a Rock to ſave himſelf.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACTUS Quintus.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> and <hi>Amidea.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe doors are faſt,</l>
                     <l>Enough is wept already for <hi>Piſano:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>There's ſomething elſe that muſt be thought on, and</l>
                     <l>Of greater conſequence: I am yet unſafe,</l>
                     <l>That for thy ſake am guilty of his blood.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though all my ſtock of tears were ſpent already<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Upon <hi>Piſano</hi>'s loſs,</l>
                     <l>Yet the remembrance that you have made</l>
                     <l>A forfeit of your dear life,</l>
                     <l>Is able to create a weeping ſpring</l>
                     <l>Within my barren head: Oh, my loſt Brother!</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt a cruel Deſtiny, my Eyes,</l>
                     <l>In pity of thy Fate, deſire to drown thee.</l>
                     <l>The Law will only ſeek thee upon Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hid in my tears, thou ſhalt prevent the ſtroak</l>
                     <l>Kills both our Name, and thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know thou lov'ſt me,</l>
                     <l>Poor Girl, I ſhall deſire to cheriſh life,</l>
                     <l>If thou lament me thus; ſo rich a comfort</l>
                     <l>Will tempt me, wiſh I might delay my journey</l>
                     <l>To Heaven.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Heaven, that we might go together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>That muſt not be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Then let me go before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Make my ſuit unto the Prince, my blood</l>
                     <l>May be your ranſome; let me dye, <hi>Sciarrha.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How my Honour bluſhes</l>
                     <l>To hear thee, <hi>Amidea?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Suffer for me! why<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou art innocent:</l>
                     <l>I have provok'd the Puniſhment, and dare</l>
                     <l>Obey it manly; if thou couldſt redeem me</l>
                     <l>With any thing but death, I think I ſhould</l>
                     <l>Conſent to live.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nothing can be too precious</l>
                     <l>To ſave a Brother, ſuch a loving Brother</l>
                     <l>As you have been.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:101820:26"/>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Death's a devouring Gameſter,</l>
                     <l>And ſweeps up all; what thinkſt thou of an Eye?</l>
                     <l>Couldſt thou ſpare one, and think the blemiſh recompenc'd,</l>
                     <l>To ſee me ſafe with t'other; or a hand,</l>
                     <l>This white hand, that hath ſo often</l>
                     <l>With admiration trembled on the Lute<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till we have pray'd thee leave the ſtrings a while,</l>
                     <l>And laid our ears cloſe to thy Ivory fingers,</l>
                     <l>Suſpecting all the Harmony proceeded</l>
                     <l>From their own motion, without the need</l>
                     <l>Of any dull or paſſive Inſtrument.</l>
                     <l>No, <hi>Amidea,</hi> thou ſhalt not bear one ſcar</l>
                     <l>To buy my life; the Sickle ſhall not touch</l>
                     <l>A Flower that grows ſo fair upon his ſtalk:</l>
                     <l>I would live, and owe my Life to thee,</l>
                     <l>So 'twere not bought too dear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do you believe I ſhould not find</l>
                     <l>The way to Heaven? Were both mine Eyes thy Ranſom,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall climb up thoſe high and rugged Cliffs</l>
                     <l>Without a hand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>One way there is, if thou</l>
                     <l>Doſt love with that tenderneſs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pronounce it,</l>
                     <l>And let no danger that attends, incline you</l>
                     <l>To make a pauſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>The Duke thou know'ſt did love thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nay, do not ſtart already, nor miſtake me;</l>
                     <l>I do not, as before, make tryal of thee,</l>
                     <l>Whether thou canſt, laying aſide thy Honour,</l>
                     <l>Meet his laſcivious arms; but by this Vertue</l>
                     <l>I muſt beſeech thee to forgoe it all,</l>
                     <l>And turn a ſinful Woman.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know the Kingdoms of the World contain not</l>
                     <l>Riches enough to tempt thee to a fall</l>
                     <l>That will ſo much undo thee; but I am</l>
                     <l>Thy Brother, dying Brother; if thou lov'ſt</l>
                     <l>Him therefore, that for thee hath done ſo much;</l>
                     <l>Dy'd his pale hands in blood to revenge thee,</l>
                     <l>And in that Murther wounded his own Soul</l>
                     <l>Almoſt to death, conſent to loſe thy innocence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! never, never<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>What, not to ſave my Life?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſtain my ſelf for ever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:101820:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where? In thy face, who ſhall behold one blemiſh,</l>
                     <l>Or one ſpot more in thy whole frame? Thy Beauty</l>
                     <l>Will be the very ſame, thy Speech, thy Perſon</l>
                     <l>Wear no deformity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh! do not ſpeak</l>
                     <l>So like a Rebel to all Modeſty,</l>
                     <l>To all Religion. If theſe Arguments</l>
                     <l>Spring from your jealouſie, that I am faln,</l>
                     <l>After a Proof you did ſo late applaud—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I had not kill'd <hi>Piſano</hi> then:</l>
                     <l>Then I but try'd thy Virtue:</l>
                     <l>Now my Condition calls for mercy to thee,</l>
                     <l>Though to thy ſelf thou appear cruel for't:</l>
                     <l>Come, We may live both; if you pleaſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who has made you afraid to dye? I pity you,</l>
                     <l>And wiſh my ſelf in any Noble Cauſe</l>
                     <l>Your Leader.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So Valiant,</l>
                     <l>I will not interpoſe another Syllable</l>
                     <l>To entreat your pity; ſay your Prayers, and then</l>
                     <l>Thou'rt ripe to be Tranſlated from the Earth,</l>
                     <l>To make a Cherubin.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>What means my Brother?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>To kill you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not fright me, good <hi>Sciarrha.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>And I allow three minutes for your Devotion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you murther me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ye tremble?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not at the terrour of your Sword,</l>
                     <l>But at the horror will affright thy Soul</l>
                     <l>For this black deed? I ſee <hi>Piſano</hi>'s blood</l>
                     <l>Is texted in thy forehead, and thy hands</l>
                     <l>Retain too many, too many Crimſon Spots already;</l>
                     <l>Make not thy ſelf, by murthering of thy Siſter,</l>
                     <l>All a Red Letter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci:</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall be the Martyr.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is there no Remedy but Death,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> then keep your word, and let me</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am</speaker>
                  <p>Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall relent.</l>
                  <l>And from your hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Forgive me Heaven, and witness <hi>I have still Kneels</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Virgin Thoughts, 'tis not to ſave my <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But his Eternal one.</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:101820:27"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha</hi> give me leave to vail my Face,</l>
                     <stage>Riſes.</stage>
                     <l>I dare not look upon you and pronounce,</l>
                     <l>I am too much a Siſter, live, hereafter</l>
                     <l>I know you will condemn my frailty for it.</l>
                     <l>I will obey the <hi>Duke.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Dar'ſt thou conſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Wounds her. [ She unvails.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh! let me ſee the Wound.</l>
                     <l>'Tis well, if any other hand had done it:</l>
                     <l>Some Angel tell my Brother now, I did</l>
                     <l>But ſeem conſenting.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, but ſeem?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>You may believe my laſt breath.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Why didſt thou ſay ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To gain ſometime, in hope you might call in</l>
                     <l>Your bloody purpoſe, and prevent the guilt</l>
                     <l>Of being my Murderer; but Heaven forgive thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Agen, agen, forgive me, <hi>Amidea,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And pray for me; live but a little longer</l>
                     <l>To hear me ſpeak, <hi>Lorenzo</hi> has</l>
                     <l>My Oath to ſend thee to his Bed: For otherwiſe</l>
                     <l>In my denial, Hell and they decree,</l>
                     <l>When I am dead, to Raviſh thee: Mark that,</l>
                     <l>To Raviſh thee: And I confeſs in Tears,</l>
                     <l>I did reſolve, when I had found thee ripe,</l>
                     <l>And neareſt Heaven, with all thy beſt deſires</l>
                     <l>To ſend thee to thy Peace.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <p>With the ſame heart I beg Heaven for my ſelf, farewel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt not die yet, <hi>Amidea,</hi> Siſter.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Florio</hi> knocks.</stage>
                     <l>I cannot come:</l>
                     <l>But one word more: Oh! which way went thy Soul?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Florio</hi> breaks open the door.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Look, here's our Siſter! ſo, ſo, chaſe her:</l>
                     <l>She may return; there is ſome Motion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Siſter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Here's <hi>Florio</hi> would fain take his leave; ſo, ſo, ſhe comes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amidea,</hi> how came this Wound?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I drew the Weapon to it:</l>
                     <l>Heaven knows, my Brother lov'd me: Now I hope</l>
                     <l>The Duke wo'not purſue me with new Flames.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> tell the reſt, love one another</l>
                     <l>The time you live together: I'll pray for you</l>
                     <l>In Heaven, farewel, kiſs me when I am dead;</l>
                     <l>You elſe will ſtay my Journey.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>She dies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Did'ſt not hear</l>
                     <l>An Angel call her? <hi>Floria,</hi> I have much</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:101820:28"/>
                     <l>To tell thee, take her up: She is not dead,</l>
                     <l>Let her alone; nay then ſhe's gone indeed.</l>
                     <l>But hereabouts her Soul muſt hover ſtill:</l>
                     <l>Let's ſpeak to that fair Spirit.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>You talk idly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do you talk wiſely then? An excellent Pattern</l>
                     <l>As ſhe now ſtands for her own Alablaſter.</l>
                     <l>Cannot thy Tears and mine preſerve her, <hi>Florio?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But we loſe time, I charge thee by thy love</l>
                     <l>To this pale Relick, be inſtructed by me,</l>
                     <l>Not to thy danger; ſome revenge muſt be,</l>
                     <l>And I am loſt already; if thou fall,</l>
                     <l>Who ſhall ſurvive to give us Funeral?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Lorenzo</hi> and <hi>Petruchio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Petruchio?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Th'art now my Servant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <p>I ever was in heart your humbleſt Vaſſal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Th'art faithful, I muſt cheriſh thy deſert,</l>
                     <l>I ſhortly ſhall reward it, very ſhortly;</l>
                     <l>Next morning muſt ſalute me Duke; the Sun</l>
                     <l>And I muſt riſe together.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſhall pray</l>
                     <l>Your Glory may out-ſhine him in your <hi>Florence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And when he ſets, we may enjoy your Sun-beam.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis handſom flattery, and becomes a Courtier.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <p>I flatter not, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then th'art a Fool:</l>
                     <l>No Muſick to a Great Man Chimes ſo ſweetly:</l>
                     <l>And Men muſt thrive; come hither, How many</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou kill'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <p>But one, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>But one?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And I muſt owe</l>
                     <l>My Life to your Lordſhip, I had been hang'd elſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But one? wait at the Door, he is</l>
                     <l>Not fit to kill a Duke, whoſe Hand is guilty</l>
                     <l>But of a ſingle Murder; or at leaſt</l>
                     <l>Not fit alone to act it: I ha' been</l>
                     <l>Practis'd already, and though no Man ſee't,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſcace the Eye of Heaven, yet every day</l>
                     <l>I kill a Prince; appear thou Tragick Witneſs.</l>
                     <stage>[He diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the Duke's Picture, a Ponyard ſticking in it.</stage>
                     <l>Which though it bleed not, I may boaſt a Murder.</l>
                     <l>Here firſt the Duke was painted to the Life:</l>
                     <l>But with this Pencil to the Death: I love</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:101820:28"/>
                     <l>My Brain for the Invention, and thus</l>
                     <l>Confirm'd, dare truſt my Reſolution.</l>
                     <l>I did ſuſpect his Youth, and Beauty might</l>
                     <l>Win ſome Compaſſion when I came to kill him:</l>
                     <l>Or the Remebrance that he is my Kinſman,</l>
                     <l>Might thrill my Blood: Or ſomething in his Title,</l>
                     <l>Might give my Hand Repulſe, and ſtartle Nature:</l>
                     <l>But thus I have arm'd my ſelf againſt all pity,</l>
                     <l>That when I come to ſtrike, my Ponyard may</l>
                     <l>Through all his Charms as confidently wound him,</l>
                     <l>As thus I ſtab his Picture, and ſtare on it.</l>
                     <l>He ſmiles, he ſmiles upon me: I will dig</l>
                     <l>Thy wanton Eyes out, and ſupply the dark</l>
                     <l>And hollow Cells with two pitch burning Tapers:</l>
                     <l>Then place thee Porter in ſome Charnel Houſe,</l>
                     <l>To light the Coffins in.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Petruchio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>The Duke's not come already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>Signior <hi>Florio</hi> deſires to ſpeak with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>This muſt retire again into my Cloſet: Admit him.</p>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Florio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>Welcome, how does <hi>Sciarrha?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He commends</l>
                     <l>His Service to your Lordſhip, and hath ſent—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>His Siſter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Much ado he had to effect it:</l>
                     <l>He hopes his Grace will quickly ſign his Pardon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſhall be done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>I have a ſuit, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>To me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Siſter would intreat your Honour</l>
                     <l>She may be admitted privately, and that</l>
                     <l>I may have Privilege to prepare her Chamber:</l>
                     <l>She does retain ſome modeſty, and wou'd not</l>
                     <l>Truſt every Servant with her Shame: Their Eyes</l>
                     <l>Are apt to inſtruct their Tongues.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>I wo'not ſee her my ſelf, command what you deſire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Y'are gracious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'll give directions inſtantly: Poor Lady,</l>
                     <l>This is the Duke's hot Blood, but Heaven convert him:</l>
                     <l>Follow me, good <hi>Florio.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>I attend, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:101820:29"/>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>Things ſhall be carried honourably<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>We are all bound to you.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Recorders. [<hi>Amidea</hi> diſcovered in a Bed, prepar'd by two Gentlewomen.</stage>
                  <p>1. This is a ſad Employment.</p>
                  <p>2. The laſt we e'er ſhall do my Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Florio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So, now you may return, it will become</l>
                     <l>Your modeſt Duties, not to enquire the Reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of this ſtrange ſervice, nor to publiſh what</l>
                     <l>Y'ave been commanded; let me look upon</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</stage>
                     <l>My Siſter now, ſtill ſhe retains her Beauty.</l>
                     <l>Death has been kind to leave her all this ſweetneſs.</l>
                     <l>Thus in a Morning have I oft ſaluted</l>
                     <l>My Siſter in her Chamber, ſate upon</l>
                     <l>Her Bed, and talk'd of many harmleſs paſſages;</l>
                     <l>But now 'tis night, and a long night with her,</l>
                     <l>I ne'er ſhall ſee theſe Curtains drawn again,</l>
                     <l>Until we meet in Heaven. The Duke already<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Duke</hi> and <hi>Lorenzo.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>May I believe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Truſt me, my Lord, hereafter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Call me no more thy Lord, but thy Companion,</l>
                     <l>I will not wear that Honour in my Title,</l>
                     <l>Shall not be thine. Who's that?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Her Brother <hi>Florio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>She is a Bed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The readier for your paſtime.</l>
                     <l>She means to make a Night on't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This ſhall declare thee to Poſterity</l>
                     <l>The beſt of Siſters—What of that? and is not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>A Brother's Life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> more precious than a Trifle?</l>
                     <l>I prithee do not ſigh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How many Ladies</l>
                     <l>Would be ambitious of thy place to night,</l>
                     <l>And thank his Highneſs? Yes, and Virgins too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>He pleads for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>He will deſerve ſome Office 'bout your Perſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>With what words ſhall I expreſs my joy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I leave you, Sir, to action. <hi>Florio</hi> is ſoon diſmiſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>He's come, good night—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>Florio?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Slave.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>My Friend, thou ſhalt be near our boſom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Pleaſures Crown your expectation.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All perfect, 'till this minute, I could never</l>
                     <l>Boaſt I was happy: All this World has not.</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:101820:29"/>
                     <l>A Bleſſing to exchange; this World! 'tis Heaven,</l>
                     <l>And thus I take Poſſeſſion of my Saint:</l>
                     <l>A ſleep already? 'Twere great pity to</l>
                     <l>Diſturb her Dream; yet if her Soul be not</l>
                     <l>Tir'd with the body's weight, it muſt convey</l>
                     <l>Into her Slumbers, I wait here, and thus</l>
                     <l>Seal my Devotion—What Winter dwells</l>
                     <stage>Kiſſes.</stage>
                     <l>Upon this Lip? 'Twas no warm kiſs. I'll try</l>
                     <l>Agen—the Snow is not ſo cold, I have</l>
                     <l>Drank Ice, and felt a numbneſs ſpread through</l>
                     <l>My blood at once—ha! Let me examine</l>
                     <l>A little better; <hi>Amidea!</hi> ſhe is dead, ſhe is dead!</l>
                     <l>What horror doth invade me? Help, <hi>Lorenzo;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Murder, where is <hi>Lorenzo?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> and <hi>Petruchio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Here, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some Traytor hid within the Chamber, ſee</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Amidea</hi>'s dead.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dead? 'Tis impoſſible;</l>
                     <l>Yet ſh'as a wound upon her breaſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <p>I prithee kill me.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>They wound him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>With all my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ha! wilt thou murder me, <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> Villain?</l>
                     <l>Oh, ſpare me to conſider; I would live</l>
                     <l>A little longer; Treaſon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A little longer, ſay ye?</l>
                     <l>It was my duty to obey you, Sir.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>Let's make him ſure, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh ſpare me, I may live and pardon thee:</l>
                     <l>Thy Prince begs mercy from thee, that did never</l>
                     <l>Deny thee any thing; pity my poor Soul,</l>
                     <l>I have not prayed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I could have wiſh'd you better prepar'd,</l>
                     <l>But let your Soul e'en take his chance.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Wounds him again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No tear prevail? Oh, whither muſt I wander?</l>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Caeſar</hi> fell by <hi>Brutus.</hi> I ſhall tell</l>
                     <l>News to the World I go to, will not be</l>
                     <l>Believ'd, <hi>Lorenzo</hi> kill'd me.</l>
                     <l>I'll preſently put in ſecurity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Will it not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am coming, <hi>Amidea,</hi> I am coming:</l>
                     <l>For thee, inhumane Murderer, expect</l>
                     <l>My blood ſhall flye to Heaven, and there inflam'd,</l>
                     <l>Hang a prodigious Meteor all thy life.</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:101820:30"/>
                     <l>Oh I faint! Thou flattering World farewell: Let Princes gathe</l>
                     <l>My duſt into a Glaſs, and learn to ſpend</l>
                     <l>Their hour of State, that's all they have; for when</l>
                     <l>That's out, Time never turns the Glaſs again.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Dies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So, lay him beſide his Miſtreſs.</l>
                     <l>The Duke diſmiſt the Train came with him?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <p>He did, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Run to <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> pray him come, and ſpeak wo' me;</l>
                     <l>Secure his paſſage to this Chamber, haſte.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Pet.</stage>
                     <l>He's dead, I'll truſt him now, and his Ghoſt too:</l>
                     <l>Fools ſtart at ſhadows, I'm in love with night,</l>
                     <l>And her Complexion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Pet.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, he's come without your Summons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Already? leave us.</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> and <hi>Florio.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Welcome, let embraces</l>
                     <l>Chain us together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Noble <hi>Florio</hi> welcome:</l>
                     <l>But I muſt honour thy Great Soul.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Where's the Duke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>They are a Bed together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>He's not ſtirring yet: Thou kil'dſt thy Siſter, didſt not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>I preſerv'd her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>So, it was bravely done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>But where's the wanton Duke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſleep, I tell you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>And he ſhall ſleep eternally.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <p>You cannot wake him, look you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Is he dead?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And in his Death we two begin our Life</l>
                     <l>Of Greatneſs, and of Empire, nay, he's dead.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>That labour's ſav'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now I pronounce, <hi>Sciarrha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy Pardon, and to recompence thy loſs.</l>
                     <l>The ſhare of <hi>Florence,</hi> I'll but wear the Title,</l>
                     <l>The Power we'll divide.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I like this well:</l>
                     <l>You told a Tale once of a Commonwealth, and Liberty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It was to gain a Faction</l>
                     <l>With diſcontented Perſons, a fine Trick</l>
                     <l>To make a Buzz of Reformation.</l>
                     <l>My ends are compaſs'd, Dam the Ribble Rabble.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Shall we Sweat for the People? Loſe our Breath</l>
                     <l>To get them fame?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'll have it given out</l>
                     <l>The Duke did kill thy Siſter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Excellent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:101820:30"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Having firſt raviſh'd her, he cannot be</l>
                     <l>Too hateful; it will dull the Examination</l>
                     <l>Of his own Death; or if that come to queſtion—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What if I ſay, I kill'd him in Revenge</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Amidea?</hi> They will pity me.</l>
                     <l>Beſide, 'twill be in your power to pardon</l>
                     <l>Me altogether.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt diſcreetly thought on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>The Devil wo'not leave us o'the ſuddain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Rare wit:</l>
                     <l>How haſtily he climbs the Precipice,</l>
                     <l>From whence one Fillup topples him to ruine:</l>
                     <l>We two ſhall live like Brothers.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Stay, we two—now I conſider better,</l>
                     <l>I have no mind to live at all—and you ſha'not,</l>
                     <l>I'll give you proof; if you but make a noiſe,</l>
                     <l>You gallop to the Devil.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm betray'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>To Death inevitable. Brother be you Spectator only.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>This is ſomewhat Noble.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thank me, not <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> I'll not engage</l>
                     <l>His Innocence to blood, thy hands are white,</l>
                     <l>Preſerve 'em, <hi>Florio;</hi> and unleſs my arm</l>
                     <l>Grow feeble, do not interpoſe thy Sword I charge thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>None to aſſiſt me? help, <hi>Petruchio,</hi> help.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                  <p>Murther, Murther!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>They fight, Enter <hi>Petruchio,</hi> who offering to run at <hi>Sciarrha,</hi> is intercepted by <hi>Florio, Petruchio,</hi> runs in crying help, <hi>Florio</hi> makes faſt the door.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Reach thy jaws wider, Villain, cry out Murther,</l>
                     <l>Treaſon, any thing; hold—Oh.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <p>falls.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you not fall, <hi>Coloſſus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Are not you hurt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sci.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know not, ha? Yes, he has prick'd me ſomewhere,</l>
                     <l>But I'll make ſure of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now muſt I follow:</l>
                     <l>I'll fight with him i'th' tother World—thy hand,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Florio.</hi> Farewell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Dies,</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He's dead too, 'tis in vain for me to fly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Within.</hi> Break open the doors.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhan't need.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pretruchio, Coſmo, Allonſo, Frederico,</hi> with Guard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſarm him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> and <hi>Sciarrha</hi> Slain?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Where is the Duke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:101820:31"/>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>Look here, my Lords.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>What, Traytor?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <p>See <hi>Amidea</hi> murder'd too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I tremble, here is a heap of Tragedies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>We muſt have an account from <hi>Florio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>He can inform you beſt that brought you hither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Lay hands upon <hi>Petruchio,</hi> diſarm him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>What blood is that upon his Sword? 'tis freſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm caught.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>To Tortures with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Spare your fury, know</l>
                     <l>'Twas the beſt blood in <hi>Florence,</hi> I muſt quit</l>
                     <l>Young <hi>Florio; Lorenzo,</hi> and my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Are only guilty of the Prince's Death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Inhumane Traytors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <p>But who kill'd <hi>Amidea?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Duke's Luſt:</l>
                     <l>There was no other way to ſave her Honour.</l>
                     <l>My Brother has reveng'd it here, but Fate</l>
                     <l>Deny'd him Triumph.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I never heard</l>
                     <l>Such killing Stories, but 'tis meet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we firſt</l>
                     <l>Settle the State; <hi>Coſmo,</hi> you are the next</l>
                     <l>Of Blood, to Challenge <hi>Florence.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pray deferr</l>
                     <l>That 'till the Morning, drag that Murtherer</l>
                     <l>To Priſon; <hi>Florio,</hi> you muſt not expect</l>
                     <l>Your Liberty, 'till all things be examin'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> now I am above thy malice,</l>
                     <l>And will make ſatisfaction to <hi>Oriana.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis a ſad Night, my Lords, by theſe you ſee</l>
                     <l>There is no ſtay in proud Mortality.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
